<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The debt book: or, A treatise vpon Romans 13. ver. 8 Wherein is handled: the ciuill debt of money or goods, and vnder it the mixt debt, as occasion is offered. Also, the sacred debt of loue. By Henry Wilkinson, Bachelor in Diuinity, and pastor of Wadesdon in Buckinghamshire.</title>
            <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 1566-1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114431</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849656</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849656</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14817</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15369)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14817)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1536:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The debt book: or, A treatise vpon Romans 13. ver. 8 Wherein is handled: the ciuill debt of money or goods, and vnder it the mixt debt, as occasion is offered. Also, the sacred debt of loue. By Henry Wilkinson, Bachelor in Diuinity, and pastor of Wadesdon in Buckinghamshire.</title>
                  <author>Wilkinson, Henry, 1566-1647.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 144 [i.e. 140], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. B[adger] and G. M[iller] for Robert Bird, and are to be sold in Cheap-side at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Errata on K7r, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans --  Criticism, interpretation, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14817:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14817:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE DEBT BOOK: <hi>Or,</hi> A TREATISE VPON <hi>Romans</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is handled: The Ciuill Debt of Money or goods, and vnder it the mixt Debt, as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is offered.</p>
            <p>ALSO, <hi>The Sacred Debt of</hi> LOVE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> HENRY WILKINSON, <hi>Bachelor in Diuinity, and Paſtor of Wadeſdon in</hi> Buckinghamſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. CHRON. 16. 9.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iehouae oculi diſcurrunt per totam ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, vt firmum ſe exhibeat erga eos quorum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus eſt integer erga ipſum.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by R. B. and G. M. for ROBERT BIRD, and are to be ſold in Cheap-ſide at the ſigne of the Bible. 1625.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14817:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14817:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY Prince CHARLES, by the grace</hi> of God, King of great Brittaine, <hi>France and Ireland, Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Faith, &amp;c.</hi> (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt gracious Souereigne:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Ebt is a thing which hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed the minds of moſt men in all ages, but the pennes of verie fewe in this kind wherein I han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle it. The Ciuilians I know tell vs what it is, and determine the caſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to their facultie worthily and
<pb facs="tcp:14817:3"/> skilfully; but to ſhew how Debt not duly and ſeaſonably paid, falles heauy vpon a mans outward eſtate, yea, and reflecteth bitterly, ſometimes vpon the conſcience, this few or none (that I know) haue hitherto vndertaken. And yet we ſee not any thing more frequent in experience, then the diſmall effects, which Debt produceth in the life of man: ſome it pierceth with perpetuall cares, ſome it impoueriſheth, ſom it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoneth, ſome it baniſheth, to ſome it cleaueth, and to their ſeede for euer, like the leproſy of <hi>Naaman,</hi> to <hi>Geha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie,</hi> till they he conſumed vtterly. It ſtayeth not heare but in ſome caſes; it ſtaineth and polluteth mens conſciences. The wages of the hireling, the portion of the Labourer in the Lords harueſt, the patrimonie of the fatherles, the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes right, kept backe by force or
<pb facs="tcp:14817:3"/> fraud, are due Debt: the cries whereof as they are entred into the eares of the Lord, ſo can they not chuſe but pierce the conſciences of the vniuſt detainers of them vnleſs they be ſeared or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſealed vp by ſome iuſt iudgement of God leauing them to their wilfulneſſe and obduration.</p>
            <p>The ordinary ſilence of Miniſters in this argument may make men thinke, perhaps, that we iuſtify, either the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of thoſe who willingly continue in the bonds of Debt, or the ſinfulneſſe of thoſe who pay them not at all. The ſinnes of the times and the vices of the ſeuerall ages of the world haue beene imputed, for the moſt part, to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Miniſters of thoſe ages and times, who by holding their tongues haue ſeemed to conſent thereunto: though it may bee they mourned for
<pb facs="tcp:14817:4"/> them in ſecret. This hath made me wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſay ſomewhat in this thing, to free myſelfe and others, whom it doth concerne, from the cenſure of poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, for ſeeming by ſilence to giue way to that which clogges a Chriſtian life otherwiſe comfortable, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable troubles and moleſtations; and to draw on others, who are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to giue their counſaile and directions for the preuenting or remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of this miſerie of Debt which hath waſted the ſtate, and perplexed the ſoules of manie thouſands in the world.</p>
            <p>This Treatiſe I haue deſired not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your Gracious permiſsion to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto your Maieſty, as the ableſt inſtrument of God, by iuſtice to reforme the vnrighteous dealing of ſuch as will not pay their Debts, and by Law to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine
<pb facs="tcp:14817:4"/> the grieuous exactions of vſuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lenders, and by mercy to relieue the miſery of ſuch as in the buſineſſe of Debt are not willing doers, but vnwilling ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers: ſuch I meane as either by the hardneſſe of mens hearts are conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at their need, to borrow vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions to them intollerable, or as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get their owne though neuer ſo due, without ſpending more then the thing is worth, in trying a doubtfull iſſue for an vndoubted right, which is the caſe of almoſt all the inferior Miniſters of the Kingdome, who cannot without ſuch coſt as they are not able to beare, recouer their due, if a couetous or craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or wilfull oppoſite will denie it. It might poſsibly haue ſeemed fitter for one of my coate to haue handled ſome matter of Faith, or tending to mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or ſome controuerſy of the times,
<pb facs="tcp:14817:5"/> theſe I know are more properly perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent to my calling, had not other men of better gifts done them abundantly with good ſucceſſe and approbation; but this argument of debt as a barren ſoyle, hath lyen vntilled like a deſolate wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe: no man regarding to reduce that into order, which hath diſordered and put out of frame the thoughts and actions of the wiſeſt men in the world. In managing wherof if I haue done the office of a faithfull Miniſter, let mee paſſe vnder the protection of your Gracious countenance; if in any thing I haue failed (as eaſily a man may doe) I humbly craue pardon, but no protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Pardon alone will ſerue his turne, who will throw the firſt ſtone at his owne error when he ſees it.</p>
            <p>In an argument of this nature its ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier to ſpeake pertinent things to men of
<pb facs="tcp:14817:5"/> lowe degree, then to Princes and Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates; the ſtate of Kings is aboue pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate capacities, and reaſons of State beyond common rules, yet my hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and prayer to God ſhall be that the cares of your Kingdoms (impoſsible to be gouerned without a moſt excellent ſpirit in your Maieſty, and ſpeciall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine aſsiſtance from God) may not bee aggrauated with the ſnares of Debt. Debt is a burden to a free ſpirited man, bee hee otherwiſe neuer ſo well able to beare it.</p>
            <p>And though it ſtand with the power and magnificence of great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces freely and daily to grant iust re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and bee alſo a more bleſſed thing to giue then to receiue, yet ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily it is counted a more neceſſary, iuſt, and conſcionable act to pay Debts, then to giue gifts: If the one at any
<pb facs="tcp:14817:6"/> time but preiudice to the other; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in them both, goodneſſe and greatneſſe, worke together: yet the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of gifts is more properly a fruit of power and greatneſſe, payment of Debts an act of goodneſſe, and true goodneſſe will then ſtand in greateſt perfection, when all earthly greatneſſe will bee laid in the duſt.</p>
            <p>The Lord of heauen bleſſe your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty with a religious, aproſperous and long Raigne ouer vs, and make you as ſupreminent in goodneſſe, as you are glorious in greatneſſe; that you may not onely long inioy theſe earthly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, but a Crowne of Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, a farre moſt excellent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding weight of Celeſtiall glory, by the onely merit of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <hi>IESVS CHRIST,</hi> to whoſe bleſsing and grace I ſhall as humble
<pb facs="tcp:14817:6"/> duty bindes mee, commend you while I liue in my truest Affections, and heartiest Prayers.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſt humble and faithfull Subiect HENRY WILKINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14817:7"/>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:14817:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE Contents of the Chapters</hi> in this Treatiſe, vpon Rom. 13. 8. <hi>Owe nothing to any man, but this, that ye loue one another; for he that loueth another hath fulfilled the Lawe.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>THe words opened, and a diſcourſe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Debts in generall, with reaſons why we ſhould not continue in them. page 1.</item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>That we ſhould owe no man any thing ſo much as lieth in vs. pag. 7.</item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>The diuiſion of Debts, and of the first kinde of ciuill Debts impoſed by others name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hereditary. pag. 10.</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14817:8"/> CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>Of legall Debts, and firſt to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. pag. 17.</item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>Of Debts to the Miniſter of the Goſpell. pag. 24.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>Of Debts to the poore. pag. 43.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VII.</label>
               <item>Of Debts procured by our ſelues, and firſt of neceſſary Debts. pag. 55.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VIII.</label>
               <item>Of voluntary Debts tranſient and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent. pag. 57.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IX.</label>
               <item>A confutation of ſuch Apologies as men pleade for their continuing in Debt. p. 67.</item>
               <label>CHAP. X.</label>
               <item>Directions for auoiding Debt that it breake not vpon our eſtate. pag. 79.</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14817:8"/> CHAP. XI.</label>
               <item>Directions how to get out of Debt, if wee be already intangled. pag. 100.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XII.</label>
               <item>Of the ſacred Debt of Loue, that we ought to loue one another, and why. pag. 114.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XIII.</label>
               <item>Of the diuerſities of loue: and of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſtian religious loue towards one another. pag. 119.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XIV.</label>
               <item>The qualities of religious loue. pag. 120.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XV.</label>
               <item>The effects of loue, with rules to diſpenſe the fruits thereof. pag. 124.</item>
               <label>CHAP. XVI.</label>
               <item>That loue is a fulfilling of the Law accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of it, and that yet hence it doth not follow: that either the perfect fulfilling of the Law is poſsible in this life: or that any can be iustified by the workes of the Law, in this ſtate of corruption. pag. 134.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:14817:9"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14817:9"/>
            <head>THE DEBT BOOKE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ROM. 13. 8.</bibl>
               <q>Owe nothing to any man but this, that ye loue one another; for hee that loueth another, hath fulfilled the Lawe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The words opened; and a diſcourſe touching Debts in generall, with reaſons why we ſhould not continue in them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the words before, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle exhorteth to render to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man his due, tribute, cuſtome, honour and feare to whom they belong, and in theſe things not to remaine debtors to any; but ſo farre as in vs lyeth to yeeld to euery man his right; from which particular enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, he proceedeth here to the generall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14817:10"/> admonition, to owe nothing to any man but loue, this is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſayth <hi>Chryſostome,</hi> a Debt neuer fully paid, but alwaies to be yeelded and alwaies due; the Argument is thus. Debts muſt bee paid, but loue is an vniuerſall and a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall debt, therefore it muſt be yeelded to all: the Verſe is reſolued into two propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, wee muſt not be in debt in ſuch things as can be diſcharged.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we muſt alwaies continue and keepe on foote the debt of loue. A reaſon is annexed of the latter Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Hee that loueth another hath fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Lawe. For the vnderſtanding of the former propoſition, we muſt conſider what Debt is. <hi>Debitum est quicquid obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatione aliqua alteri praestatur:</hi> Debt is whatſoeuer is performed to another, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any bond or reaſonable conſideration: Now as is the obligation, ſuch is the debt; obligations are of three ſorts, of Nature, of Grace, and of Ciuill contract. Bonds of Nature and Grace are perpetuall, ſo long as the parties remaine, as a child ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a perpetuall reſpect to the Parents,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14817:10"/> and they to him, euen by nature: ſo Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are vnited in the bonds of grace, which muſt not faile but ought to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue. Yet the ciuill bonds of debt, which come by borrowing and lending, by buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling, or any interchangeable duties and ſeruices, doe then ceaſe when they are payed and performed. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is to be vnderſtood of this third kind of debt as we may ſee by the excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Text, which keepes that debt on foot which cannot totally be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               <p>Now when he ſayth, Owe nothing to any man, I took it not to be a ſimple pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of all ciuill debts, which cannot bee auoided, while humane contracts ſtand; but it is an admonition duly and truly to diſcharge all ſuch debts, and ſo much as in vs lyeth, not to continue in them. <hi>Hortatur,</hi> ſayth <hi>Chryſoſtome, vt nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius rei quám ſolius dilectionis debitores ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neamus, ſoluentes ſcilicet quicquid rerum aliarum aut officiorum debemus.</hi> He exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that wee remaine not debtors of any thing, but of loue only, paying forthwith whatſoeuer other things or duties wee do
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14817:11"/> owe; this doth <hi>Bucer</hi> follow, and other the beſt Expoſitors.</p>
               <p>The inſtruction is this: That whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ciuill debts or duties we owe to any, we muſt truly and duely pay them, and ſo much as in vs lyeth not continue vnder that bond and obligation. Giue vnto <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> that which is <hi>Caeſars,</hi> is an excellent rule, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 21. and is it not euen as true and as good; render to your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour that which is your neighbours? If the work-man be worthy his wages, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 7. then euen the hireling muſt haue his due; the pooreſt labourer his due; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the labourer in the Lords harueſt. If it be a brand by Gods Spirit vpon the wicked, that he borroweth, but paieth not againe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 21. Then ſhould euerie good man, ſo much as in him lyeth, pay euery man his owne, and not willingly continue vnder the bond of debt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe debt conſumes many a <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> mans eſtate, by the hard conditions vpon which they are conſtrained to borrow; as vpon vſurious contracts, or vpon cruell bargaines, or vpon ſuch pawns and Morgages and Obligations as vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14817:11"/> vndoe a man in the forfeiture.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in many caſes it is a ſeruile <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thing to be indebted: and therefore when the Lord will ſet downe an vnderling, hee deſcribes him by being a borrower, and not a lender. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. 43. <hi>Hee ſhall lend to thee, but thou ſhalt not lend to him. Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> is more peremptory; <hi>The borrower is a ſeruant to the lender,</hi> Prou. 22. 7. ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them equall before, as we may ſee by his ſubmiſſiueneſſe and flatteries, and obſequiouſneſſe, and ſeruile obſeruations. By Debt a mans ſtate and perſon is in a manner mancipated to the lender. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, gifts for loane of money, make free men ſeruants, by tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as I conceiue, the ſtate of him that ſo borroweth, from freedome to ſeruility.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by long continuance of a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> debt, freely lent, the Lender may be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified greatly by the Borrower. A man by trading and turning the Stocke, may raiſe maintenance to himſelfe, and ſuch as depend vpon him; whereas the money in another mans hand long deteined, is like aburied Talent, in reſpect of the owner.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Debt may prooue vncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14817:12"/> fortable to a mans owne Conſcience, for what if payment be ſo long deferred till a man be not able to pay? till he be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ingage others? what if it be defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red till a man dye? then that which might haue beene ſatisfied by ones ſelfe, will ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hardly bee diſcharged by his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. A man well able to pay his owne debts, may leaue an Heire that ſhal not be bound to pay. Lands pay no debts, or not in haſt; not at a mans neede.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, a man indebted cannot (while he ſo continueth) liue comfortably, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, though otherwiſe frugall and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious, yet hee enioyeth not the labour of his hands, but he ſoweth, and another reapeth; or hee reapeth to another that which he ſoweth: he earneth wages, but another mans bag muſt bee filled with it, and ſo he laboureth for the winde; ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when hee borrowes vpon vſury, for that will eate out all a mans increaſe. Nor can a man thus continuing, prepare to die contentedly, by ſetting his houſe and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſtate in order. For, if debts muſt firſt be paid, as vndoubtedly they ſhould, and then Legacies and Portions, what
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14817:12"/> certainty can be aſſigned to the fatherleſſe and widow, when whatſoeuer is moſt precious in a mans houſe or ſubſtance, muſt bee drawne out to the ſatisfying of the Creditour, before they can bee ſure that they eate their owne bread? Many men ſeeming rich, are found poore and naked, when euery bird hath her owne feather.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>That we ſhould owe no man any thing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeſe grounds being thus laid, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as the words lead me.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.] Two negatiues in other languages make an affirmatiue, in the Greeke, <hi>Duae negativeae plerum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiús negant,</hi> two negatiues for the moſt part doe more vehemently denie, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: in this place in hand, each negatiue hath it's ſeuerall weight, for if we muſt owe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to no man, then <hi>ſuum cuique redde,</hi> pay e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man his owne: if we muſt owe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, then wee muſt pay all fully, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14817:13"/> at an vnder-value, out of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of pouertie.</p>
               <p>Firſt, be indebted to no man, ſo much as in you lyeth: not to a rich man, leaſt he draw you before the Tribunall: not to a poore man, leſt his maintenance detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned be a crying ſin in you: not to a Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, leſt hee take occaſion to root out you and your Family: not to a Tenant, leſt his ſtocke in our hand, which might haue been improued vnto profit, make him fall ſhort in paiment of his rent: not to a Miniſter, leſt hee be impoueriſhed, and inſtead of hoſpitality to others, be caſt vpon the curteſies of a mercileſſe world: not to the fatherleſſe and widow, leſt in the bitterneſſe of their ſoule and ſenſe of their want, they make their moane to God, who wil certainly iudge their cauſe: not to a ſeruant leſt he bee diſcouraged, and put vpon ſhiftes vncomfortable to himſelfe, vnprofitable to you. Owe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to a friend, leſt you be burdenous where you ſhould be helpfull, or leſt fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of payment proue a ſhip-wracke of friendſhip: not to a foe leſt he exact rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly, and worke vpon ſome vantage:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14817:13"/> Owe not to a Neighbour, leſt you loſe your liberty: not to a Stranger, leſt you fall into ſome ſnare: not to a buyer, leſt you diſapoint his owne neceſſity: not to a Seller, leſt hee enhance the price of his commodity: not to a free Lender, leſt you diſable him from managing his own affaires: not to an Vſurer, leſt he conſume you as a Cankar. Wee ſhould owe no man any thing, if wee be in caſe to pay it; no not our owne Fathers, to whom wee ſhould, <hi>vicem rependere,</hi> make requitall rather then run further vpon that skore. By making too bold, euen with parents in this kind, many men haue loſt their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry patrimony.</p>
               <p>There is in borrowing, a kinde of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious ill-liberality, which an ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirit brooketh not, if there be any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remedie. Beſides, there is ſuch a corruption in the hearts of men, that euen a free lender will thinke hee may well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the fruite of his beneuolence ſome other way, and that makes him ceaſe to bee a free lender. Laſtly, by deepe and great debts, there is ſuch a world of cares vpon the heart of the debtor, that it
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14817:14"/> breakes his ſleepe, it diſtempers his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and afflicteth him ſo continually, that <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> hearing of a man that died exceedingly in debt, deſired to buy the Pallet or Bed vpon which a man ſo deepely indebted could ſleepe; intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereby, that great debt is ſuch a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſiue as is able to moleſt the minde of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, euen of an Emperour, and to make it reſtleſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3. <hi>The diuiſion of debts, and of the first kinde of debts, impoſed by others, namely, Haereditary.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Owe nothing.] That our proceeding may be ſuch, as hee that runnes may read it. Let mee here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound in a ſhort diuiſion, the ſubſtance of the enſuing diſcourſe, touching civill and mixt debts, which fal firſt to be hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Debts are either impoſed by others, or procured by our ſelues. Impoſed by others, are hereditarie, or legall. Legall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14817:14"/> are of three ſorts, to the Magiſtrate, to the Miniſter, or to the Poore. Debts procured by our ſelues, are either neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, or voluntary. Voluntarie are either caſuall and tranſient, or permanent and ſtanding debts: The remedies whereof are either ſuch as preuent, or ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue the diſeaſe: Of all which in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The ſacred debt of Loue is alſo to be handled in the ſecond propoſition. But firſt of Hereditary debts, which are the firſt kinde of ciuill debts impoſed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Theſe are ſuch as Parents impoſe vpon their Heires, or Teſtators vpon their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors by will and teſtament; or which neceſſarily fall vpon the ſtate of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed. A Teſtament or Will, is; <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vlpian in d. lib.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>noſtrae iuſta ſententia, de eo quod poſt mortem noſtram fieri voluerimus.</hi> A Teſtament is a iuſt declaration of our will, touching that which we would haue done after our death. By this a man may haue a calling to the paiment of debts and legacies; &amp; conſequently vnto debts which cannot perhaps with comfort, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not without loſſe to himſelfe and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14817:15"/> others bee auoided.</p>
               <p>Now if a man, in regard of the truſt repoſed in him, and of the meanes alot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for performance of the ſame (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, and his owne acceptation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring, no man ſtands charged) will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the execution of any mans Will, then muſt he accompliſh what is enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and preſcribed, by the true meaning of the Will, according to <hi>Auſtins</hi> rule; <hi>Aut Teſtatoris voluntas ſeruanda, aut haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditale carendum.</hi> Either muſt the Will of the Teſtator be obſerued, or the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance muſt be loſt. In debts then thus impoſed, this remaineth to be done; We muſt pay them ſpeedily at the time pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed, leſt they loſe their acceptation, by hanging too long in our hands: Wee muſt alſo pay them faithfully and fully, without keeping backe from any that which is intended to them.</p>
               <p>Among things which paſſe by Will, beſides that which is giuen to kindred and friends, there are ſometimes ſummes of money and yearely penſions alotted to Colledges, and Schooles of learning, to Hoſpitalls, and High-waies, to the poore
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14817:15"/> of certaine pariſhes, and to other godly vſes, and then the debt ſo to bee paide, is not meerely ciuill, but a mixt debt: of a common nature in reſpect of the matter, as money or goods; but in reſpect of the godly &amp; pious vſe, of a higher ſtraine. In all theſe we muſt deale truely and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, both with the dead, and with the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: For as the counterfetting and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <note place="margin">Lege Corn. de falſis.</note> of a falſe Will, was puniſhable an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently in ſome caſes by death, in ſome by baniſhment and publication of goods: ſo the ſuppreſſing of a true will, by not publiſhing or not performing it, to thoſe whom it doth concerne, is a ſinne and an iniquity, not much inferior to the other: the one iuſtifies a dangerous lye, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conceales a neceſſary truth, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out periury perhaps in both. It was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Dauids</hi> complaint; <hi>Defecerunt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>races</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 12. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>a filiis hominum.</hi> The truſtie are fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the ſons of men. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint is ſtill iuſt, in this particular as much as in any. I am perſwaded very few Wills are executed by the common ſort of men, in eſtates of any value, without ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table fraud, partly by alledging (when pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14817:16"/> ſhould be made) defect in the ſtate, and partly by concealing legacies from thoſe who cannot demand them, out of ignorance of the Will; to whom I ſay, that ſo long as wrong reckoning is no pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the debt remaineth in the ſight of God, how euer it bee croſſed out of their accounts. They ſhall alſo finde, that <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 16. 11.</note> for being vnfaithfull in the diſpenſation of earthly talents, they ſhall neuer bee truſted with the true treaſure. It may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo one day be their owne caſe, that as they haue cancelled and made void the Will of the dead, by deteining debts and lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies from the right owners, ſo by the iuſt iudgment of God, the like <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 7. 2.</note> meaſure may be meated to their widowes and father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe children, by thoſe whom they ſhall vnworthily put in truſt: wee may not thinke an account diſcharged, when a fraud and a deceit is cunningly contriued. A debt cannot bee paid but by reall ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, without which the obligation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in full ſtrength and force; vpon the conſcience whereof, an honeſt heart cannot but bee tenderly ſenſible: And therefore I am not of <hi>Cyprians</hi> minde,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14817:16"/> who tooke order; <hi>Ne quis Clericum tuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyp. Epiſt.</hi> 66.</note> 
                  <hi>aut curatorem teſtamento conſtitueret.</hi> That none ſhould appoint a Clergie man Guardian or Executor by Will, leſt hee ſhould bee moleſted with the affaires of this life. I rather thinke that men ſhould bee choſen out of all vocations and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings whatſoeuer, of moſt vnſtained con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation and conſcience moſt alienated from couetouſneſſe, leaſt intangled in worldlineſſe, for the diſpenſation of our eſtate to whom it is intended.</p>
               <p>Before I leaue this point, let mee ad one caueat to Parents and Teſtators, not to charge their Wills with that which their ſtate cannot diſcharge; for this is the way either to haue nothing done at all, or to expoſe their executors or ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors to perpetuall ſuites and clamours. A man were better ſell all that he can ſpare, and pay his owne debts himſelfe, then out of an ambitious humour of leauing ſo much in lands to his Heire, lay withall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him ſuch a maſſe of debts &amp; legacies, as ſhall mancipate him to the ineuitable yoake of the Vſurer, till hee can redeeme himſelfe, by ſelling what is moſt precious
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14817:17"/> in his patrimonie: which when one is compelled to doe, let him then conſider whether the great poſſeſſions which came to him by inheritance, were not partly the ſpoile of the Church, the prey of the poore, and the fruits of oppreſſion, which like <hi>Aurum Toloſanum,</hi> the gold of Tolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aul. Gel. lib.</hi> 3.</note> makes euery hand vnfortunate, into which it comes: let him alſo well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whether the intollerable maſſe of debt, be not that vnmoueable yoake, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by <hi>Micah,</hi> and threatned to them <note place="margin">Micha 2. 2. 3.</note> who couet fields, and take them by force, who roote out men and their families, threatned, I ſay, to them, and their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Let them laſtly conſider, whether a ſmall thing to the righteous man be not <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 16.</note> better, then great riches to the wicked and mighty; howeuer ſome of them floriſh till the meaſure of their iniquity be at the full. Thus of the firſt kinde of debts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by others: the next are Legal.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14817:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. 4. <hi>Of Legall debts; and firſt to the Magiſtrate.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE debts impoſed by humane laws and ordinances, are of diuers ſorts, as Subſidies, Fifteenes, Tenths, Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and other penſions to the Church or to the Common wealth, in peace or in warre. Theſe are common burdens, which euery man in his place muſt neceſſarily beare. as a member of a politicke body, and readily for auoiding offence and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation iuſtly enſuing vpon neglect. Theſe fall due either to the Magiſtrate, ſpecially to the Kings Maieſtie, or to the Miniſter, or to the Poore. In all theſe I know there is a morall right, and ſo they may be called morall debts, in reſpect of the common ground of diuine or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall iuſtice: But we call them legall debts, <hi>Secundum regulam legis determinantis,</hi> in reſpect of the Law, determining thus much to ſuch a man, of ſuch a calling, at <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin. pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, ſecundae queſt.</hi> 99. <hi>art.</hi> 5.</note> ſuch a time: it's <hi>Aquinas</hi> his diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14817:18"/> The ground of ſuch debts as come to the Magiſtrate, is from divine Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though for the manner and meaſure of them determinable by law. For if the Magiſtrate be Gods Miniſter (ſo is hee <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4. 6.</note> called both <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) if for our wealth, if for the puniſhment of euill doers, and praiſe of them that doe well, if hee labour and attend continually vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this thing, is there not an equity ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the conſcience, that ſuch a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſo ordained of God for ſo excellent a ſeruice, ſhould haue his reward? Or doth not the Apoſtle conclude inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly? <hi>For this cauſe pay wee tribute,</hi> Rom. 13. 6. and Ver. 7. pay therefore tribute, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, feare, honour to whom they are due. Miniſters of Peace and Iuſtice, as they ſhould not conſume their inferiours: (for ſo the remedie will be worſe then the diſeaſe) ſo ſhould they not be conſtrained to ſpend vpon the ſtocke, &amp; to waſt their owne eſtate further then as members of eminent ability, ſhould beare a burden for the common good, proportionable to their ſtrength. But Magiſtrates ought to haue Tributes and Penſions of their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14817:18"/> inferiours, as pledges of ſubiection, as recompences of ſeruice, and as meanes to defray expences for the publike good; euen equity and neceſſity requires all this.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe in Monarchies (the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of earthly gouernments, and types of the heauenly) the King is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Gouernour, not onely ouer all perſons, but in all cauſes, Eccleſiaſticall and Ciuil, to ſee them done and managed according to Gods will, by Officers qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified with gifts and callings requiſite for ſuch matters: And ſeeing theſe Officers of eminent place and truſt, at home and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, are imployed immediatly by the Kings Maieſtie, and conſequently main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by him that ſets them on worke; hereupon it is, that by vertue of ſome lawes perpetually in force, and by vertue of ſome Statutes, deuiſed for ſupply of caſuall occurrents, beſides the power of Prerogatiue Royall, Tributes and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, Subſidies and Tenths, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other penſions fall due to the King, and ſo are counted legall debts, though morall in their originall, yet legall, <hi>ex de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminatione</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14817:19"/> 
                  <hi>legis,</hi> the Law preſcribing how it ſhall be for quantity and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. In paiment whereof, it is the wiſdome of our State, that though where nothing is to be had, the King muſt loſe his right, yet hee ſeldome doth loſe any thing of that which is found due by Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers employed &amp; put in truſt; and it were pitty it ſhould not come entirely into his treaſury. For how ſhould the moſt illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious eſtate of ſuch a Monarch? how ſhould ſuch miniſters of State, of Iuſtice of Peace, peareleſſ (I am perſwaded) for worth and wiſdome? How ſhould ſuch a Navy? ſuch men and munition as muſt be alwaies in a readineſſe againſt caſuall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents? how ſhould ſuch Armies as may be requiſite in a tumultuous and raging world be maintained at his coſt? how ſhould true Religion, and the Goſpell ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely preached, (for which the world hates vs, and yet without which our life would be tedious, and a very ſhadow of death) bee defended by his power againſt the malice of the Diuell and his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if all the ſprings and fountaines of the Kingdome, did not conſtantly runne
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14817:19"/> into the Ocean of his Treaſury?</p>
               <p>As our Nation hath not beene back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the payment of this debt, ſo hath it beene more happy then any nation in the world, in our two laſt Soueraignes, Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>Iames,</hi> both of bleſſed memory, to whom it hath been paied. For, beſides protection by the Sword of Power and Iuſtice, common to other Subiects (yet not euery where ſo common as were to be wiſhed) wee haue had the true Faith of Ieſus Chriſt profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the preaching of the Goſpell eſtabliſhed and countenanced by publike Authority, for the ſpace of ſixtie ſix years without interruption. A moſt ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bleſſing, for which we owne euen our ſelues vnto them, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes to <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Philem. v. 19.</note> and for which none but God onely can make recompence. The Children that now are ſhall not forget King <hi>Iames</hi> when they are old; the Elder alſo ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence his memory, becauſe by his princely care, and expreſſe direction, for Catechizing the ignorant, not onely the younger are able to giue an account of their Faith; but euen the elder, though
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14817:20"/> vnwilling to appeare, <hi>ſenes elementarij,</hi> old men learning principles, yet they do both countenance the worke by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and doe encreaſe daily in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and zeale.</p>
               <p>Thus our two late gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes, moſt memorable for great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but for none ſo much, as in that they were an incomparable payre for defence the true Faith, and propagation of the Goſpell, haue had (as they deſerued) the loue of our hearts, &amp; a reall performance of thoſe pecuniary debts whereof I ſpeak, and ſhall be had by vs and ours in an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting remembrance: which wee doubt not ſhal daily be renued by that moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble branch ſpringing from that roote ſo bleſſed to our Nation, our deare Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord King CHARLES, that now is. Concerning whom wee cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the greatneſſe, either of our hopes, or ioies which wee conceiue. For his life, hitherto vnſpotted of the world, ſo free in youth from the luſts of youth; ſo farre from intemperance in the fulneſs of plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; ſo preualent ouer pride in ſuch a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; ſo vnſtained by Popery in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14817:20"/> ſchoole of Spaine; ſo attentiue and iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in hearing Gods word; ſo full of goodnes when it was not in requeſt; ſuch a life, I ſay, hitherto in the bloſſome and ſpring doth promiſe precious fruits in the ripeneſſe and maturity.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed are thoſe guides, liuing and dead, who had the ſeaſoning of ſuch a veſſell of honor and grace, and failed not in the ſeruice: and bleſſed is his Majeſtie, who in his Chriſtian education laid ſuch a foundation of religion and wiſedome, of godlineſſe and honeſtie; as is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable ioy and comfort of all his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſubjects, and will bring him infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in a courſe of holineſſe, to a perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life and happineſſe at laſt.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour pleads the right of <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 22. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> euen then, when <hi>Tiberius</hi> a ſubtle Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant was that <hi>Caeſar. Paul</hi> in this place doth moſt earneſtly vrge the paiment of Tributes and all other duties to the Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior powers at that time when <hi>Nero,</hi> whom elſe-where he calls the <note n="*" place="margin">2. Tim. 4. 17.</note> Lion, was the Roman Monarch. What elſe doth this teach vs, but that how-euer the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of gouernors may at ſome time
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14817:21"/> be grieuous in exacting; yet the ſubject, (if releaſe cannot bee had by ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) muſt be alwaies obedient in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to the vttermoſt of his ability. How much more ſhould we hauing by the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious prouidence of the Almightie, ſuch a King ſet ouer vs, as we truſt will proue a man after the heart of God; as <hi>Dauid</hi> did in Iſrael, and a pattern of grace and zeale, as <hi>Ioſuah</hi> was in <hi>Iudah:</hi> How much more, I ſay, ſhould wee moſt cheerefully yeeld vnto him the homage of our hearts, the ſeruice of our hands and the portion of our ſubſtance required by Law to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt mite: beſides, our continuall prayers vnto God for his preſent and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture happineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5. <hi>Of Debts to the Miniſter of the Goſpell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANother debt impoſed by humane Ordinance pertaineth to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, as Tythes and other penſions in the right of the Church. Theſe I cal, impoſed by humane Lawes, not as wauing the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14817:21"/> claime by Diuine right (till I bee other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe inſtructed then yet I am): For, if Tythes were due to the Prieſt of the moſt high God <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 14. 20 Gen. 28. 22.</note> paid by <hi>Abram;</hi> if vowed by <hi>Iacob,</hi> before the Law giuen in mount <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reb;</hi> if they were due vnder the Lawe, to the Prieſts and Leuites, by diuine right for the ſeruice of the Tabernacle; If a maintenance bee due to the miniſters of the Goſpell, as the Apoſtle pleadeth pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. from <hi>verſe</hi> 7. to the 15. &amp; <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 6, 7. If God haue ordained, that they who preach the Goſpell ſhould liue of the Goſpell, and that hee who is taught in the word ſhould communicate vnto him of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is taught in all good things: then ſurely I ſee not, but that tythes at leaſt, or ſome better thing, ſhould be due to the Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell by Diuine Ordinance; and that thoſe who take them from vs, ſhould giue vs a better thing, as thoſe who vnder the Law had a mind to redeeme their tythe, were bound to ad to the price euery <note n="*" place="margin">Leuit. 27. 31.</note> fift pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie aboue the true value. But I make it not my taske to diſpute this queſtion, my betters haue done it lately and worthily.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14817:22"/> I here conſider tythes, and other portions of the Miniſters maintenance as a legall debt due by a double right. Firſt, the faithfull labourer in the Lords harueſt is worthie his wage, <hi>ex debito,</hi> not <hi>ex gratia,</hi> by debt, not by curteſie; though he be <note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 7, 8, 9.</note> but an earthen veſſell, yet his treaſure is verie precious, and his Miniſterie much more excellent then that of the Law.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that hee ought to haue the tythes in kind by vertue of the poſitiue Law of our kingdome, moſt agreeable and conſonant to the Originall Law of God, <note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 4, 12</note> in lew of his ſeruice for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of the Saints, and for the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the body of Chriſt by the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Goſpell; ſo that it is not a meere Legall but a Morall debt, as I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of that to the Magiſtrate out of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas.</hi> A mixt debt, ſo let me call it, becauſe the ſeruice is holy, and the things miniſtred are ſpiritual, though the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence bee temporall goods or money. I need not cite the words of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Henry</hi> 8. <hi>an.</hi> 27. and 32 <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>an.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> Statute, the practiſe is paiment, vnder paine of triple damage, euen in Impropriations, where the worke is not done by him that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14817:22"/> takes the wages. What then can bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged why this debt ſhould not bee paid? So aſſigned by God, who holds his work-man <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 10. 7.</note> worthy his wages, as well in the New Teſtament as in the Old; ſo confirmed by Law, proportioned to the <note n="*" place="margin">Numb. 18. 21, 22. 24. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> authenticall patterne; ſo dearely earned by the continuall paines of the faithfull Paſtors, who haue the moſt dreadfull charge of Soules. I ſpeak not for Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietaries, they will be ſure to ſhift for themſelues. I put the caſe with all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour that may be, yet not otherwiſe then ſtands with the truth in many places.</p>
               <p>That which they anſwere for non-pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this debt, is, that they owe vs no ſuch matter; for <hi>Debitum est quod iure ab inuito exigi poteſt:</hi> That is a debt which may lawfully be required of a man againſt his will; but this cannot ſo be exacted ſay they: for their land is Abby-land, and conſequently exempted as was the Abby; or their land is freed by compoſition, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription or cuſtome: and for theſe they will ſtand, <hi>tanquam pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> as for their altars and their houſes, indeed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their altars and houſes of God, To
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14817:23"/> whom I ſay not any thing to plead for the belly, as they ſuppoſe: If I had the tongue of the eloquent and learned, their bellies would haue no eares to giue mee audience in ſuch an Argument; I ſpeake onely for diſcharge of my owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in ſeruice of the truth, and to cleere my ſelfe for euer from conſenting vnto ſacriledge in any man, or matter.</p>
               <p>Firſt, their land is Abbey-land, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Places ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt.</note> to ſuch a Monaſtery before the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; ſo let it bee, and ſo let them enioy it, vnleſſe it be a thing conſecrated to the Church; if ſo, then except they be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, or Prophets Children, or ſuperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Leuites (who alwaies had their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance and portion in things conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) or in the nature of theſe, let them take heede and looke well to themſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a ſnare to deuoure that which is holy, &amp; after the vowes to make enquiry, <hi>Pro.</hi> 20. 25. It is an ancient Canon; <hi>Semel dicatum Deo, non eſt ad humanos vſus vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriús</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De reg. iuri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in Decr. reg.</hi> 51.</note> 
                  <hi>transferendum:</hi> That which is once dedicated to God, is not to be tranſlated afterwards to the vſes of men: That is, if it be conſecrated rightly to the ſeruice of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14817:23"/> God it may not be alienated to the priuate common vſes of men, not employed in that ſeruice; ſome few caſes are excepted, whereof this is none. To this they will ſay, That they finde themſelues hereof poſſeſſed by inheritance, and they haue digeſted it already well enough. If God be pleaſed with it, I wiſh them all proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; their lot is fallen to them in a fayre ground: they haue a goodly heritage: yet I had rather haue my part in a lot leſſe diſputable. But, admit all is well, and that they hold what they haue without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcruple, I enuy not vnto them the leaſt dramme of their right. But, what doth become of the Tyth of thoſe lands? are not thoſe more ſpecially conſecrated in their original, &amp; in their vſe more proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary to the maintenance of Gods ſeruice then the Lands themſelues? Why then is the payment of theſe denied? and in lieu thereof, ſome pitifull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible penſion ill paied, to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable defacing of the Miniſtery in that place.</p>
               <p>The ſame Authority, ſay they, which giues Miniſters the Tythe in places not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14817:24"/> exempted, hath exempted our lands from payment of Tythes in kind; thus we haue it, and ſo we meane to hold it.</p>
               <p>I diſpute not the power of Princes and Parliaments, it is aboue my capacitie, and out of my element, I alwaies yeeld to Law, preſuming reaſon of ſtate in it, though I ſee it not. But what if the Law be not ſo cleare as is imagined? The aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Tythes, (which came to the King at the diſſolution of Abbyes, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the lands) was at firſt an Act of the Pope, by an iniurious vſurpation vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the right of the Church, and againſt the Lawes of God and man then in force. If this were in the Pope a ſacrilegious Act, hatefull to God, who deteſteth rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie <note place="margin">Eſay 61. 8.</note> in the ſacrifice, it is not to bee thought, that our Statute Law intended, to iuſtifie that in any which is ſacriledge in the Pope; or to make that iuſt, which is originally vniuſt. I do not thinke that our Statute Law intended, either to aboliſh Tythes vtterly, or to decide the right, but to change the poſſeſſion for the preſent time, till the claime of the Church might more euidently appeare. But ſuppoſe the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14817:24"/> Law for non-payment of theſe Tythes were as cleare as the practiſe, yet as in the buſineſſe of the Tabernacle, <hi>Moſes</hi> was admoniſhed, <hi>See thou do all things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 25. 40. Hab. 8. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>to the patterne ſhewed thee in the mount:</hi> ſo in matters of the Church, all things ſhould be done, chiefly in matters of importance, according to the patterne of holy Scriptures. Now whether the Law enioyning Tythes in generall, or the Act releaſing that payment to ſome, bee more agreeable to the Originall patterne, let any man iudge that is not a partie. For mine owne particular, when I find it pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually ſet downe, That as <hi>thoſe who mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9. 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>about holy things, did liue of the things of the Temple, and they which waited at the Altar, were partakers of the Altar, that ſo the Lord hath ordained, that they who preach the Goſpell, ſhould liue of the Goſpell:</hi> Me thinkes it hard dealing, that we ſhould be barred of the benefit of the ancient ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Tythe, till ſome other Law of prouiſion diſanulling the former can bee produced out of the Scripture.</p>
               <p>Another exception againſt true pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <note place="margin">Compoſition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> euen where lands are not exempt,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14817:25"/> is compoſition with the former Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bents. Of this kinde I haue heard many pretended, but I could ſcarce euer ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny produced, leſt ſome thing of aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ſhould relieue the preſent Miniſter, which ſhewes the obnoxious diffidence of a guilty heart, when the cauſe is nought; for otherwiſe men are forward to make proofe of their right, for ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſuch as haue iuſt cauſe to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. But ſuppoſe a compoſition as firme as couetouſneſſe and craft can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe it, I would gladly learne, how it ſtands with conſcience or common ſenſe, that the act of an Incumbent onely for terme of life, remoueable vpon preferment, or miſdemeanour, ſhould preiudice his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor in a place of painfull ſeruice, to the vtter impoueriſhment and vndoing of all poſteritie? Is it poſſible, that in any law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full contract, the fruit of the godly and religious labours of a free and ingenuous man, in the Lords harueſt, ſhould bee bought and ſould before he is borne, by thoſe who are meere ſtrangers vnto him? Or if this cannot bee done in any godly and righteous courſe, why ſhould not the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14817:25"/> ancient rule take place; <hi>Quae contra tus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, pro infectis haberi debent:</hi> That thoſe things which are done againſt right, ought to be eſteemed as if they had not beene done. The old word is, <hi>Caueat Emptor,</hi> let the buyer looke to it: but I thinke, both the buyer and ſeller, being in this caſe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in euill, had neede to looke to it, leſt they ſwallow that in earth, which they ſhall digeſt in hell; I doubt it will one day be a cold comfort to thoſe who are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to ſuch an act, to conſider vpon their death-bed, that by their ſinfull hands the Church is depriued, for the time preſent and to come, of what ſoeuer hath fallen within their power to diſpoſe of. Can that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue any hope to be found a true member of the Church triumphant in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that liues &amp; dies a betrayer &amp; ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the Church militant here on earth?</p>
               <p>Preſcription is another mouſell of the <note place="margin">Preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Oxe that treadeth out the Corne: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall of this worke of darkeneſſe is commonly thus; There are few great rich men to be found, that can indure with patience to pay any Tyth in kinde; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they take their opportunity, when
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14817:26"/> ſome Miniſter is incumbent, either not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to doe the worke, or not reſident, or ſome other way obnoxious, to agree with him for their Tyth at an vnder-value, a pound perhaps in the hundreth, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that they can vſe the matter ſo, as that the Tyth ſhall bee little or nothing worth vnto him; yet this yearely penſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they will allow for zeal to the Church, and good will to the man, whom they will not ſticke to mollifie with comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or with any thing elſe that ſhall coſt them nought: theſe conditions are continued from the father to the child, by the ſame arts and practiſes, till a new man come to be preſented, who for quietneſſe ſake muſt take things as he finds them; or if he dare contend, they will ſcourge him through all the Courts of the kingdome. When thus it hath beene caried for two or three deſcents, though men know in their conſciences, that, <hi>Non firmatur tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu temporis, quod de iure ab initio non ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtit:</hi> That it gets no validity by tract of time, which is not grounded vpon right from the beginning: yet from theſe deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full practiſes thus continued, preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14817:26"/> doth ariſe to put the Miniſter to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſilences, who hauing ſpent his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony in the Vniuerſitie, hath neither time nor money nor euidence on the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine to mannage the Churches right, though a preſcription once begun, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume it daily more and more. For if the preſcribers adde by purchaſe or incloſure to their demaines within the ſame Pariſh, the thin and ill-fauoured preſcribed pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, like the <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 41. 4, 7.</note> thin eares of corn, and lean Kine in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dreame will ſwallow vp all the Tythe of the portions ſo annexed, and be neuer a whit the fuller.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, if the preſcribers chance to ſell, its no ſauoury bargaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Tythe be included, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter excluded out of that portion, and confin'd to ſome ſmaller peece of ground more proportionable to his pitifull pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The time was when our Sauiour <note place="margin">Ioh. 2. 14, 15, 16.</note> in a feruent zeale caſt buiers and ſellers out of the Temple, what will he doe one day to thoſe who thus couetouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croach vpon the patrimony of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?</p>
               <p>Cuſtomes are no leſſe pernicious to <note place="margin">Cuſtomes.</note>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14817:27"/> the ſtate of the Miniſter in keeping backe his due, then theſe; for as theſe exempt ſome particular perſons or places in great matters, ſo cuſtomes ſwallow all ſo far as they goe like a generall Deluge; if they find a Benefice like the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> they will leaue it like a deſolate wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I ſpeake of ſuch as are pretented vpon vſage without any euident reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable cauſe, whereby the Churches pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony is moſt iniuriouſly detained: and why ſhould not euery man that is able to oppoſe reaſon and truth againſt them, cry them downe? For though it be true that <hi>diuturni mores conſenſu vtentium compro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bati</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iuſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>legem imitantur,</hi> that manners long continued, and approued by conſent of ſuch as haue vſed them are a kind of law; yet conſent and practiſe is not enough to giue a cuſtome the power of a lawe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be <hi>conſenſus rationabilis,</hi> a conſent grounded vpon reaſon, <hi>niſi enim conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo ratione munita ſit, non est conſuetudo, ſed corruptela:</hi> If cuſtome be not fortified by reaſon, it is not a cuſtome but a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. Now it will be hard to proue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon in the thing or conſent of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14817:27"/> Miniſter, who is alwaies a party in thoſe things which are obtruded as cuſtome vpon the Church. If men will ſweare that it is their cuſtome to pay no tyth wood, then you muſt haue none, though the greateſt part of the Pariſh bee wood-ground<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If men will ſweare that it is their cuſtome not to pay tyth Wooll, for ſheep not wintered in the field, then you muſt haue none, though they haue a full ſtocke that takes I benefit of the Common for eight the moſt profitable moneths of the yeare; but it may bee you ſhall haue ſome proportionable rate: nothing leſſe, but ſome ſuch contemptible ſcraps as are not worth the gathering vp; which how it ſtands with reaſon, or the good liking of the Miniſter let wiſe men iudge. Yet if men will affirme vpon oath that theſe and the like are the cuſtomes of their Pariſh, wee haue no remedie; and cuſtomes ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome fail for lacke of ſwearing. If theeues had come vnto thee; if robbers by night, would they not haue ſtollen that which were enough for them? If Grape-gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers had come to thee, would they not have left ſome Graps, <hi>Obadiah, verſe</hi> 5.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14817:28"/> but cuſtomes ſweepe all away, they leaue in a manner nothing. The Church, ſaies <hi>Auſten,</hi> diſcourſing of cuſtomes, being <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuar. Epiſt.</hi> 119.</note> placed in the midſt of many Tares, and much Chaffe, tollerates many things; <hi>Et tamen quae ſunt contra fidem, &amp; bonam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam non approbat, nec tacet, nec facit:</hi> yet ſuch things as are againſt faith &amp; a good life, it neither doth approoue, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale, nor practiſe. The like ſay I in this, the Church, whoſe cauſe I plead, tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerates many preſſures, ſuſteyneth many iniuries; but cuſtomes againſt all reaſon and right, againſt iuſtice and common ſenſe, it neither approueth, nor concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth; nor practiſeth the like it ſelfe towards others.</p>
               <p>When the malignity of all theſe exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, compoſitions, preſcriptions and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, like ill conſtellations, bring penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and miſery vpon the Clergie. When theſe foure come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, like the foure ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ſorts of Vermine mentioned by the Prophet, the Palmer-worme, the Locuſt, <note place="margin">Ioel 1. 4.</note> the Cankar-worme, and the Caterpiller, the latter ſtill conſuming the reſidue of the former, is it not time to mourne and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14817:28"/> complaine when out meat is cut off be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, and ioy and gladneſſe from the houſe of our God? <hi>Ioel</hi> 1. 16. Is it not time to ſay with <hi>Amos, O Lord God</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Amos 7. 2</note> 
                  <hi>forgiue we beſeech thee, by whom ſhall Iacob ariſe, for he is ſmall. Querelae</hi> (ſaies one) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Liuius l.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>ne tam quidem grate, quanda fortaſſe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> Complaints are not then wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come when perhaps they are neceſſary; but it were better to complaine, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh, and reproue, then that a curſe ſhould reſt vpon vs as it did vpon <hi>Iudah,</hi> for robbing God in Tythes &amp; Offerings, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 8, 9. If anſwer bee made, that the caſe is not like; I confeſſe it is not like in many circumſtances, but it is very like, if not the ſame, in ſubſtance: For if God haue as peculiar an intereſt in vs, and as fatherly a care ouer vs, as in and ouer the Miniſters of the Law; then, if the defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Prieſts and Leuits were ſacriledge in the Iewes, how<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>euer the ſtile and word may bee mittigated; yet our curbing the Miniſters of the Goſpell by force or fraud, will proue ſomething which cannot bee anſwered in the day of account.</p>
               <p>In this point I had much rather referre
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14817:29"/> the Reader to the godly Sermons of the moſt learned Doctor <hi>Raynolds,</hi> vpon the Prophecie of <hi>Obadiah,</hi> ſpecially vpon the 5. and 6. Verſes, then ſay any more my ſelfe; onely let me adde theſe few things: Firſt, let that of <hi>Ieremy</hi> be wel conſidered; <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord againſt the Ammonits,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 41. 1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>hath Iſrael no Sonne? hath hee no heire? why then doth the Ammonite poſſeſſe God, and dwell in his Cities? Behold I will cauſe the alarme of war to be heard in Rabbah, of the Ammonits, and it ſhall be an heape, and his townes ſhall be burnt with fire, and Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el ſhall bee heire vnto them that were his heires, &amp;c.</hi> Let mee now enquire as God did of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>God;</hi> hath <hi>Leui</hi> no ſons? or hath the Miniſter of the Law no heire? why then doth the Lay man poſſeſſe the Clargie? Why doth hee encroach vpon the portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Miniſter of the Goſpel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Remember the imprecation vpon the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Leui,</hi> Deut. 33. 11. <hi>Smite through the loynes of them that riſe againſt him, that they riſe not againe.</hi> The Lord turne the hearts of the ſpoylers of his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, who doe not now as the Iewes, <hi>Agg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> 1. 4. neglect the houſe of God to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14817:29"/> build their owne, but take away the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance &amp; reuenues of Gods houſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large their owne. The old word was, <hi>Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas redde &amp; diues ſis,</hi> pay tythes that thou maieſt be rich: &amp; it is <hi>Ieromes</hi> obſeruation, <hi>Decimi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> redditis vbertas, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> redditis fames fuit;</hi> That there was plenty when Tythes were paied, &amp; penury whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were not. But the preſent practiſe is, pay not Tythes that thou maieſt be rich; &amp; it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now, that its all one, whether Tythes be paid or not, &amp; that the Lord in that reſpect will doe neither good nor ill. Is there then no difference betweene the cleane and the vncleane? or betweene well gotten goods, and the wages of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity? If vnder the Law a man otherwiſe <note place="margin">Agg. 2. 14.</note> cleane, did hold in his hand a thing pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted and vncleane, if he waſhed himſelfe neuer ſo oft, yet he was ſtill vncleane: all the water in Iordan, and the ceremonies of Leuiticus could not clenſe him, ſo long as the polluted thing remained in his hand. The Miniſters portion wrongfully vſurped and vniuſtly deteined from him, is an vncleane thing in the hand of the oppreſſor, who ſo long as hee holdeth the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14817:30"/> vncleane thing in his poſſeſſion, cannot but bee polluted and vncleane in Gods ſight. The Lord I truſt will at laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue the vaile of ignorance and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe from their hearts whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes, that they may ſee the breaches which they make vpon Gods Miniſters, and will giue them true repentance and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, that their ſinne may bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen, and their polluted conſciences purged in the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to them by a liuely Faith; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Lord in mercy thoſe who haue compaſſion on the daily ruines and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caies of thine houſe, and let not the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bee wiped out which they ſhew to thine houſe, and to the Officers thereof. Thus much of the Legall debt to the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, which I take not to be meerely ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, but a mixt Debt, becauſe though that which is yeelded be a temporall thing, yet it is the compenſation of a ſpirituall ſeruice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:14817:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. 6. <hi>Of Debts to the poore.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Third kind of debt impoſed by Law, is to the poore: the burden hereof is laid vpon the richer ſort, according to their ability. I ſpeake not now of almes which is voluntarie and left to diſcretion; yet required in <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 15. 10, 11.</note> Scripture with much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity: but of ſuch monies as are pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by vertue of the Law, made in the dayes of Queene ELIZABETH, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reg. Eliza.</hi> 43. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> continued in the reigne of King IAMES of bleſſed memorie for the raiſing of a ſtocke to ſet the poore on worke, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuing of the lame, impotent, blind, aged, and ſuch as are not able to worke, and for putting out of poore children to be pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, which euer being not only pollitike but godly alſo and religious. I hold the debt not meerly ciuill, but a mixt debt, as was the former: for the chearfull and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy paiment whereof let me vſe theſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:14817:31"/>
               <p> Firſt the care which God hath had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies for the poore: Hee doth not only plead their cauſe <hi>Deut,</hi> 15. 10, 11. And o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen thy hand liberally to thy brother, to thy poore, to thy needy; for euen for this cauſe the Lord thy God ſhall bleſſe thee in all thy worke, and in euery thing that thou putteſt thine hand vnto; but he allots a portion of the third yeers Tythe, not only to the Leuite (who neuer is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded) but to the ſtranger, the fatherleſſe and the widow; <hi>Deut.</hi> 26. 12. As <hi>Hierome</hi> hath obſerued vpon <hi>Ezech,</hi> 45. and calls it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the poore mans Tythe. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p>God allotted them a portion in his own lot and portion: when God takes order that euery thing may not bee taken as a pledge, not the vpper or nether milſtone, <hi>Deut.</hi> 24. 6. and that if a poore man lay his garment to pawne, it ſhall be reſtored before the going downe of the Sun, <hi>Exo.</hi> 22. 26. Doth not this reſtraine from offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring hard meaſure to the poore in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity? Beſides, wee know, that as the poore lye open to the greateſt iniuries, men treading downe where the hedge is loweſt: ſo God takes ſpeciall notice of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14817:31"/> wrong done vnto them, he denounceth his iudgements againſt ſuch as doe <hi>concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere tenuem,</hi> ſhake them to pieces, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> did <hi>Naboth,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 21. Such as take their corne from them, <hi>Amos</hi> 5. 11. Such as grind their faces, <hi>Eſay</hi> 3. 16. as root them out and their families: <hi>Mic.</hi> 2. 1, 2, 3. Hee alſo counts a ſcorne to them, a contempt to himſelfe; <hi>Prou.</hi> 17. 5. <hi>Who ſo mocketh the poore, reproacheth his Maker;</hi> let not vs therefore deny them their right, whom the Lord doth take into ſuch ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall protection, as to interpret a kindnes or vnkindnes to them, as done vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Let vs alſo remember that this is Gods will and appointment, that the poore ſhould alwaies bee in the Land, for exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their patience, and tryall of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher mens beneuolence, and his own glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie out of them both. For the abilite of the one being accommodated to the neceſſitie of the other; thankeſgiuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God ariſeth from them both, as from the Phyſitian and the Patient when a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily cure is done. Wee muſt not thinke that when the cauſe of the poore is ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14817:32"/> and ſo tenderly in the Scriptures commended to the rich, that all this adoe is for a pennie now and then to a begger when we liſt; but it is to draw vs to a wiſe conſideration, how the ſtrong may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the weake, how wee may beare one anothers burthen, and as fellow members ſerue one another through loue, that the wealth of one ſupplying the want of the other, there may be no defect. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when ſuch Lawes are deuiſed and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by authoritie, as inioine a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of Gods reuealed will, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the poore of the Land, in ſuch ſort, as may be comfortable to them and eaſie to vs, ought wee not moſt willingly to pay this debt both in reſpect of God and of man?</p>
               <p>A ſecond motiue to the paiment here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is the prouiſion of the godly in former ages for the poore. In the Primitiue Church Deacons were appointed for the daily miniſtration of neceſſarie things, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 1, 2. <hi>Paul</hi> ordained in the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Galatia</hi> and <hi>Corinth,</hi> that on the firſt day of the weeke euerie one ſhould lay by in ſtore, as God had proſpered him
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14817:32"/> for reliefe of the poore, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 1, 2. How earneſtly alſo doth hee exhort the Corinthians to liberality towards the poore Saints, by the example of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians, who had beene beneficiall to their power and aboue their power, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8, 9. This I mention to ſhew, that the more the Goſpel was embraced, the more bountifully was Chriſt relieued in his members. When after the bitter ſtormes of perſecution, the Church in ſucceeding ages had reſt, then were Hoſpitals erected and endowed with reuennues, that the poore might both be harboured and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed: They had alſo receptacles for the ſicke. The firſt founders of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> kind, was <hi>Fabiola, prima omnium</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>inſtituit in quo aegrotantes colligeret deplateis, et con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpta languoribus atque inedia miſerorum membra foueret, Hieron Epitaph Fab. Fabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ola</hi> was the firſt of all that built a recepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle for the ſicke, into which ſhe might ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the diſeaſed out of the ſtreets, and might cheriſh the bodies of poore wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, conſumed with languiſhing and famine.</p>
               <p>Our owne Nation wanteth not exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14817:33"/> of this kinde, which I rehearſe to this purpoſe, that the voluntary contributions of Gods religious people in all ages, may make vs more willing to beare the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary burden impoſed by law as a debt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs. If our hearts and hands had not beene ſtraitned too much this way, there had been no neede of compulſory means; but, <hi>Ex malis moribus bonae leges:</hi> For the hardneſs of our hearts was this law made. Out of the ſinful defect of Charity in the greateſt part of men, hath ariſen a legall impoſition of this duty, that many hands might make lighter worke. Some I know we haue, who may truly ſay with <hi>Iob;</hi> that, They haue not reſtrained the poore of their deſire; that they haue not cauſed the eies of the widow to faile: who haue not eaten their morſells alone, but the fatherleſſe hath eaten thereof, <hi>Iob</hi> 31. 16, 17. Some there are who in the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and poore, haue entertained, <hi>Chriſtum conuiuam,</hi> euen Chriſt as a gueſt, as <hi>Hierom</hi> ſpeakes it. But there are others againe of competent wealth &amp; ſtate, who the more they haue, the leſſe good they will doe, and ſo long as they were left to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14817:33"/> would neuer touch the burden with the leaſt of their fingers: and now that they are compellable by law, it's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible to heare how they quarrell at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Leuey, how they make the Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors attend, how they grudge againſt the poore, adding ſorrow to their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, forgetting that of <hi>Paul; That God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a cheerefull giuer:</hi> 2. Cor. 9. 7. And that of our Sauiour too; that, <hi>It is a more bleſſed thing to giue then to receiue:</hi> Act. 20. 35. whom I would mitigate, if they were tractable, with theſe conſiderations, as further motiues to pay this debt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they beare not the yoake alone, but ioyntly with others of their owne ranke, as equally laid vpon them as indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent men can deuiſe it: wee muſt pay ſcot and lot (as is the word) vnleſſe we will be, <hi>Homines nullius cenſus,</hi> Men of no account. Secondly, this payment to the poore is not made to maintain idleneſſe, the mother of luſt, a ſinne of <hi>Sodome;</hi> but to raiſe a ſtocke to ſet ſuch to worke, who would otherwiſe bee vnprofitable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the earth, liuing on the ſpoile, not eating their owne bread; whereas a ſmall
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14817:34"/> contribution out of euery hand a little to raiſe a ſtocke, doth take away the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon euaſion of idle perſons; I haue no worke, therefore I muſt beg or ſteale. A ſtocke will finde them worke, and a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent hand at worke will not onely feed, but alſo enrich. That which makes vs tremble at the multitude of the poore, (and ſay with the Prophet; <hi>Thou haſt mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 9. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>the nation, but not encreaſed the ioy)</hi> is, our failing in ſetting the poore to ſuch worke as they are able to doe, for want of a ſtocke alwaies in readineſſe to keepe them imployed. Thirdly, whereas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny true labouring men are not able by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence &amp; aſſiduity to ſupport the weight of their charge: by the paiment of this debt, opportunity is offered to raiſe them vp who ſink vnder their burden, &amp; who in ſenſe of their neceſſity, hauing made their moane to God, will bee thankefull for a ſupply to him and to vs. Our plenty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing applyed to our brethrens want in ſuch a caſe, is like precious ſeed, ſowed vpon good ground, tilled and prepared; wee need not doubt of an encreaſe at harueſt. Fourthly, wheras many are aged and paſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14817:34"/> their worke, blind, impotent, diſeaſed; by the paiment of this debt, we are helpefull vnto thoſe whom it were ſin and ſhame to forſake. <hi>Hic, ad cuius intuitum nobis vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. Epit. Fab.</note> 
                  <hi>erumpit, noſtri ſimilis eſt, de eodem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum formatus luto, ijſdem compactus ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis:</hi> this man, at whoſe preſence our ſtomacke is turned, is like vnto vs, formed of the ſame clay, and compoſed of the ſame elements; whatſoeuer hee ſuffers, we may ſuffer the ſame our ſelues: <note n="*" place="margin">Eſay 58. 7</note> Turne not then thine eies from thine own fleſh. Whereas the viſiting of theſe would bee very tedious vnto vs, yea impoſſible, by true paiment of this little, wee are, <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes per altena miniſteria,</hi> mercifull to them by the miniſtery of others, which in our perſons wee could not ſo well bee. Laſtly, whereas the breeding of poore children in families of ſmall imployment and rude education, doth vtterly cut off all proofe and hope; by the payment of this allowance, impoſed by law, diligent and diſcreet Officers are inabled to bind them to occupations anſwerable to their capacity, that ſo as good plants, tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from a barren to a better ſoyle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14817:35"/> profitable &amp; fruitfull; ſo theſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted from idleneſs &amp; rudeneſs, to a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of employment and diſcipline, may be of vſe and ſeruice, both in peace and warre. I am perſwaded, the wiſeſt of vs cannot tell, how to diſpenſe ſo ſmall a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as goes from vs by this meanes, to ſo many excellent purpoſes, when the Statute is duely executed; and if it faile in execution, the fault is not in vs, if the debt be truely paid. Let it not then bee tedious to vs to doe ſo much good, with ſo little coſt or loſſe, if that can be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted loſſe, which being ſowen on earth, we ſhall reape in heauen. When wee ſee wicked men ſo violent in doing ill, as Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors and Idolaters daily are, ſhould not we be aſhamed to be weary of doing well? <hi>Quale hoc eſt, cumpeccatores in malis</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron in Epiſt. ad Gal. cap.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>operibus quotidie augeantur, vt nos in bono opere laſſemur:</hi> What a thing is this, that when ſinners are ſtrengthened in euill workes, we ſhould be weary of our well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.</p>
               <p>I ſpeake not any thing in this diſcourſe for the vagrant Rogues and Beggers of our nation, they are the Sodomits of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14817:35"/> Land, without God, without Magiſtrate, without Miniſter, Children of <hi>Beltal,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out yoake, none can rule them, nor make them aſhamed, though they liue in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious luſts. <note n="*" place="margin">2. Theſ. 3. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that will not labour, ſhall not cate,</hi> ſaies <hi>Paul,</hi> yet they will eate the ſweat of other mens faces, though they be idle and vnprofitable, and to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good worke reprobate; theſe I leaue to ſuch extremity as the Law of God and man laies vpon them: <note n="*" place="margin">Prou. 31. 8.</note> I open my mouth for the dumbe, who will not ſpeake for themſelues, and for the godly poore, who had rather be helpefull then chargeable to others; and for the aged and impotent, whoſe miſery moues compaſſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an Oratour. For theſe I ſpeake, who if there were no Statute of prouiſion to enforce the paiment of this debt, or to direct the vſes, yet haue a iuſt claime to the almes of the rich, &amp; the rich hath ſuch an intereſt in them, as that they are called as well their needy, and their poore, as their brethren, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15. 11. which I chiefly vnderſtand of thoſe, who being ioyned to vs by vicinity or affinity, are by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence put vpon vs, as a part of our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14817:36"/> charge, to whom, <hi>Eleemoſinas non facere crimen habentis eſt,</hi> Hier. <hi>in Pſal.</hi> 112. to theſe not to giue almes were a ſin in him that hath where withall; ſo that if there were no law at all, yet there is ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in the thing, and ſuch a neceſſity in the poore, that a rich man ought to bee a law vnto himſelfe; hee ought in this caſe, to <note n="*" place="margin">Prou. 3. 9.</note> honour God with his ſubſtance, which cannot be better done, then by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to ſuch as want it, the fruit of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence. I ſay not as ſome doe; that, <hi>Eleemoſiua est debitum,</hi> that almes is debt; which in ſome ſenſe may be true; but, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the law requireth a portion of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, ſeeing there is an equity and a pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the thing, ſeeing the neceſſity is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, <hi>The poore yee ſhall haue alwaies with you,</hi> Mat. 26. In this concurrence of law and conſcience, the non payment of this debt is vncomfortable and ſinfull. Thus of legal Debts, which for moſt part are not ſimply ciuill, but mixt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:14817:36"/>
               <head>CHAP. 7. <hi>Of Debts procured by our ſelues: and first of neceſſary Debts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DEbts impoſed by others, hauing hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto beene handled; now follow in order, Debts procured by our ſelues: theſe are either neceſſary, or voluntary. Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary are ſuch as could not by diſcretion or induſtry be preuented, nor diſcharged by any meanes within our power. Put caſe a mans houſe, which hee is bound to repaire, as being tenant to another, bee vtterly conſumed with all his ſubſtance by caſualty of Fire, the condition of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, which is alwaies reaſonable in ſuch contracts, brings vpon this man a neceſſary debt, which neither could bee preuented before, nor performed in this caſe, which by Gods prouidence is befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len him. Suppoſe a man in time of dearth haue ſpent all his money, and cattell, and ſubſtance whatſoeuer; his lands alſo for bread: It was the caſe of the Egyptians in <hi>Ioſephs</hi> time; what remedie hath he, but <note place="margin">Gen. 47.</note>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14817:37"/> to run in debt, though hee mancipate his very body for the payment. If theſe ſeeme (as indeede they are) vnuſuall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, let vs conſider things more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Whena a mans wages, which hee can earne, are ſo ſmall, and his domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call charge ſo great, as that the one cannot ſupport &amp; ſuſteine the other; then comes Debt, as a wayfairing man ſpeedily, and as an armed man violently, that will not bee kept off. This, as I conceiue, might be the caſe of the man of God, the poore Prophet, who feared God, and yet dyed in debt, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 4. 1. and it is the caſe of many a poore man, whoſe whole family depends vpon his induſtry and frugality; hee riſeth early, and late takes reſt, and eates the bread of care, yet cannot for all this liue out of debt. Some men alſo turne from one trade to another, from husbandry to grazing, from that to mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing, <hi>Vt mutando induſtriam mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron. in Eſaie.</hi> 43.</note> 
                  <hi>infaelicitatem, nihilominus diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one dei, his quos ſaluare dignatur, omnia ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentibus eueniunt contraria;</hi> Though men by changing their employment would change their hard eſtate, yet by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14817:37"/> of God, euen to thoſe whom he vouchſafes to ſaue, all things fall out croſſe when they haue tried all the waies. Theſe debtors, thus enforced by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to groane and to ſtruggle vnder the burden, are to be pittied by the lender, to bee releiued by the giuer, and God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly will requite it.</p>
               <p>This Debt is no ſinne, nor any other pecuniary debt of it ſelfe, but a croſſe it is: in ſome, a puniſhment of ſinne, in all, an exerciſe of patience, and a diſcipline of humility, and ſo, <hi>Paupertas ſalutaris,</hi> a wholſome kinde of pouerty, teaching men to lay vp treaſure in heauen, when things here vpon earth frame ſo little to their contentment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8. <hi>Of Voluntary Debts, tranſient and permanent.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VOluntary Debts are ſuch as might at firſt haue beene auoided, or ſatisfied and paied within ſome time conuenient, yet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were incurred notwithſtanding and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14817:38"/> continued, either to ſerue our turne for ſome profit, or perhaps for ſome delight; or, it may be, for reliefe of others in ſome extremity. I cenſure not all theſe with a note of reproofe, they may ſometimes be helpefull in compaſſing gainfull bargains, yea, in ſupplying the wants of ſuch as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhift for themſelues; thoſe only I miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like which entangle men in worldly cares, in wilfull ſnares, and vnſupportable loſſes; and yet ſerue but to the ſatisfying of ſome fooliſh luſt when all is done.</p>
               <p>Theſe voluntary debts are either caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and tranſient, or permanent and ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. It is a caſuall debt which any man may incurre, <hi>Ex re nata;</hi> out of ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſudden occaſion. <hi>Dauid</hi> is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God to offer a Sacrifice to the Lord, in the Threſhing-floare of <hi>Arauna</hi> the Iebuſite. <hi>Dauid</hi> will not offer of that which ſhall coſt him nought, he therefore <note place="margin">1. Chro. 21. 25. 2. Sam. 24. 24.</note> buyes the Threſhing floare at a price by it ſelfe for 600 ſickles of gold, and the Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en for 50 ſickles of ſiluer: after this bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine made, it was a caſuall Debt of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> till the money was paid, which I know was done ſpeedily: yet in euery bargaine
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14817:38"/> of ſale accompliſhed, as the buyer hath a property in the thing ſold, ſo oweth he a debt till paiment be made, be it ſooner, or later. Without theſe caſuall debts, the life of man doth not conſiſt, and in theſe, as a man needes not to bee ſcrupulous in making vſe of a friend for a ſhort time, ſo muſt he be exact &amp; punctuall in keeping day; not keeping time makes a iar in pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as well as in muſicke. He muſt alſo be cheereful in doing the like courteſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, whether it bee lending or forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. That which I call a tranſient debt, is alwaies like, often the ſame with this; when a man owes ſomewhat to a worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or a Tradeſman, for a ſhort time, or to a Seruant for his wages, till a ſet day, it is a tranſient debt, daily running and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing among men, and not ſetled or perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in reſpect of time. In theſe we muſt be honeſt, and reall, and truſty, and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. For as the Graſhopper is a burden to the aged: ſo a little thing deteined, or not duely performed, may be a troubleſome diſappointment to the poore (and the greateſt part are poore) and may afflict them by tedious delaies, when money
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14817:39"/> hangs too long in the hands of ill pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters.</p>
               <p>As for permanent and ſtanding debts, theſe are indeed, <hi>fundi calamitas;</hi> theſe breake downe as it were the blade of corn in the field; theſe, like wormes &amp; moaths, fret out a mans eſtate, be it neuer ſo firme and ſound at the firſt. This commeth, when men able to giue ſecurity, borrow great ſummes of money or wares, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either purpoſe or poſſibility of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, within any competent meaſure of time; and it is commonly procured, either out of a couetous deſire of purchaſing whatſoeuer lyeth conueniently; or out of a prodigall and riotous humour of ouer-ſpending vpon luſts and curioſities; or by giuing more for a caſuall preferment then a man is worth; or by ſome other groſſe failing in iudgment; or indiſcretion about the diſpenſation of our eſtate.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the lamentable conſuming debts, with which, when a mans credit is rent and torne, as it will be very quickly, then muſt the ancient inheritance bee morgaged, then muſt their beſt and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt friends be ingaged, then Seruants and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14817:39"/> Tenants muſt be brought to the ſtake, and bound for more then they are worth; then muſt depopulations and racking of rents, and defrauding of Miniſters be put in practiſe, and yet all too little, becauſe <hi>Amalecke,</hi> the licking people, I meane the nation of Vſurers and their Factors, as Cormorants fall vpon the borrower. Then the debt is multiplied when the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uennues are diminiſhed, and the Vſurer conſumes all a mans encreaſe. Let no man continue in the Vſurers book for one and twenty yeares (as ſome are neuer out while they liue) for, a hundred pound, paying intereſt vpon intereſt, after ten pound in the hundred, (ſuppoſe nothing giuen to Scriueners and Broakers, yet for his hundred pound) hee ſhall pay in that time ſix hundred &amp; ſorty pound, beſides the principall, as appeares by calculation; which makes mee wonder why any man ſhould open his mouth for vſury, which thus opens her mouth, and enlargeth her bowells like hell, to ſwallow the poore Borrower.</p>
               <p>Let thoſe who plead this cauſe conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that God diſpenſeth with no vſury,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14817:40"/> when <hi>Neſhek</hi> the biting, and <hi>Tarbith,</hi> which they call the toothleſſe Vſury are both condemned, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18. 8. 13. that the lender, for eight or fiue in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, deales not as he would be delt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, for hee himſelfe would neither giue eight, nor fiue, nor two, if he could bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row freely; and the rule of loue is, To doe to all men as wee would they ſhould doe to vs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 12. Let them conſider, how Vſury is cried downe, among other op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15. 5. How it is condemned by the Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Concil. Nic. Cap.</hi> 18. <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Ruffin. can.</hi> 17.</note> in Clergie-men, as matter of filthy lucre, (if filthy lucre in Miniſters, then no righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous dealing in others.) How it hath beene the vtter ruine of many thouſands in our Nation; how in the Church of Rome at this day, all Vſurers are excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated monethly; how no man of note in all antiquity (Iewes &amp; Manichees excepted) none I ſay of honeſty and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for fifteene hundred yeares after Chriſt hath euer vndertaken the defence hereof: wherfore as <hi>Ioaſh</hi> ſometimes ſaid <note place="margin">Iudg. 6. 30, 31.</note> to the men of <hi>Hophra,</hi> when they ſtood for <hi>Baal</hi> againſt <hi>Gideon, Will you contend</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14817:40"/> 
                  <hi>for Baal? let him plead his owne cauſe:</hi> ſo ſay I to the patrons of Vſury; Will you contend for <hi>Mammon?</hi> let him plead his owne cauſe. Shall <hi>Tirus</hi> and <hi>Zidon</hi> riſe <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 21.</note> vp in iudgment againſt <hi>Corazin</hi> and <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaida,</hi> for not bringing fruit anſwerable to their meanes? And ſhall not the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts riſe vp in iudgment againſt vs for practiſing that oppreſſion, which they, who walke not by ſo cleere a light, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne? Let the Borrower himſelfe alſo conſider the vnſatiable Daughters of the <note place="margin">Prou. 30. 15</note> Horſleech, that ſucke him, and deuoure the ſweat of his face, the fruit of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, induſtry, and skill. If the King ſhould take out of the poore mans ground three of his beſt Kine yearly, or ſo many horſes out of his Teame, would hee not crye, that he muſt needs giue ouer houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping, and husbandry? Yet, the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower of 100 pound from yeare to yeare, ſuffers, in effect, all this which I ſay, at the hands of the Vſurer, and dare not ſpeake a word againſt his conſumer; but onely ſuffers and giues thankes. If one word of diſcontentment fall from him, then muſt the ſtocke bee ſold, that ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14817:41"/> may be made, leſt any aduantage of forfeiture be taken. If an vſurious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract for ſo ſmall a ſumme, make ſuch a breach into a mans eſtate, what will the borrowing of thouſands doe for many yeeres together? When I ſee any man of eminent place and worth, caſt vpon the Vſurer (whoſe mercies are cruel) for grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters then he is able to weild, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but interpret it as a diſmall ſigne of ſome fatall ruine to the family: or, at leaſt of ſome notable defalcation of eſtate, for cauſes beſt knowne to God, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times apparant to the eies of the world.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, this ſoaking and ſtanding debt, doth ſo exerciſe and afflict ſome men deepely engaged, that it takes vp bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtudies &amp; meditations, it ſpends much precious time in ſolicitation of Broaker, Lender, and Suerties; it leaues no free time for praier &amp; repentance; it drownes the comforts which men otherwiſe might enioy, when they ſee how debt conſumes them day and night; yea, and continues ſtill, without any diminution of the ſum. Much perhaps ſome borrowers haue in lands, and in revennues, in poſſeſſion and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14817:41"/> expectation, but as <hi>Alexander</hi> the great ſomtimes ſaid: <hi>Quid refert ſi multa habeam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch in Alex.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; nihil agam,</hi> what matters it if I haue much and doe nothing? So ſay I, what is one the better for a great eſtate; if debt bind his hands, from doing good to the poore anſwerably, from prouiding for younger children, from reſtoring the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters right?</p>
               <p>If a man out of debt will doe more good with a hundreth, then a man vnder the Vſurers chain with a thouſand pound a yeere, yea and much more chearefully. Let vs then bee thus farre indulgent to our ſelues, as to ſhake off the deadly yoak of Billes and Obligations, which manci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate the moſt free and ingenuous ſpirit, and drie vp the very fountaines of libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. Yea, they ſo put a man out of aime, that he cannot ſet his ſtate in order, but liues and dyes intangled and puſled with cares and ſnares; and after a tedious and laborious life paſſed in a circle of fretting thoughts, he leaues, at laſt, inſtead of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter patrimonie a world of intricate trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to his poſteritie, and to his ſureties, which cannot be mannaged by thoſe who
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14817:42"/> vnderſtand them not but to great diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage.</p>
               <p>When <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts and Monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 1692. <hi>col.</hi> 2.</note> Arch-biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> (as is recorded in his life, by reuerend M. <hi>Foxe)</hi> diſcerned the ſtorme which after fell vpon him in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, he tooke expreſſe order for the paiment of all his his debts; which when it was done a moſt ioifull man was he, that hauing ſet his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires in order with men, he might conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate himſelfe more freely to God. This ſhould teach vs all in this tumultuous and raging world, to free our ſelues ſo much as is poſſible, from the bonds of debt to men, that wee may more freely and conſtantly performe our duties and vowes to God, which will otherwiſe be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, if not vtterly aboliſhed by wordly cares and moleſtations; if wee giue them intertainment, as wee cannot chooſe but doe, ſo long as wee are in debt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:14817:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. 9. <hi>A confutation of ſuch Apologies as men plead for their continuing in debt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat the Apoſtles counſell of owing nothing to any man may the better be followed: three things remaine to be added to this diſcourſe. Firſt, I would ſhew the vanitie of thoſe Apologies, which men haue deuiſed for continuing in debt. Secondly, how to auoid it that we come not into it. Thirdly, how to get out of the ſnare if wee be intangled.</p>
               <p>That debt is a conſumer of credit and ſtate, of goods and good name; howeuer ſome men thinke the contrarie, yet there is no queſtion to be made. How ofter do we ſee, that as after the biting of an Aſpe, the man ſmitten fals aſleepe, but the poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon diſpearſeth it ſelfe through euerie member till the whole bodie be poiſoned: So after debt contracted, ſpecially vpon the hard tearmes of vſurie, or ill conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the debter is lulled a ſleepe by the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14817:43"/> ſweetnes of the preſent ſupply, but the debt paſſeth as a poiſon through euery part of a mans ſubſtance, <hi>donec totum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertatur in debitum,</hi> till all be turned into debt, it is <hi>Chryſostomes</hi> compariſon. Yet <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Matth.</hi> 5</note> for all that; as the dropſie-man delighteth in abundance of drink, though moſt hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in that diſeaſe, becauſe it ſatisfies the preſent appetite: ſo men in debt alreadie are willing to continue, yea to multiply the ſame, (becauſe thereby their preſent need is ſerued) though it be neuer ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious in the concluſion. Let vs ſee their allegations and accordingly determine.</p>
               <p>Firſt they hold it lawfull without all <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Allega∣tion. </seg>1</label> queſtion, to borrow when they can, and thinke it conuenient, and make no ſcruple at all to continue in an vſurious debt for many yeers together; and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly ſo far and ſo long as they can giue ſecurity, they will neuer by their good wils come clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of debt: for howſoeuer they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the lender vpon vſurie, at leaſt in their conſciences, though they dare not tell him ſo; yet they take the borrower to be cleere, and rather to bee pitied then cenſured by any. But in this, as I take it,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14817:43"/> they are deceiued. For, though the caſe may ſo be put, that a man may borrow, and ought to borrow, euen vpon vſury, if there bee no other remedy; as, when money is payable vpon forfeiture of a Leaſe, or of a Bond, or of a mans liuing; and the party that owes it, is vtterly and ſuddenly diſappointed by another; then is hee, by the reaſon of the hardneſſe of mens hearts, who will not helpe him at ſuch a need, ineuitably caſt vpon the Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, as chuſing of two euills of loſſe the leſſe: Yet, to ſticke and to continue in the Vſurers furnace, which will leaue a man at laſt neither mettle nor matter, I hold it to bee vtterly againſt prudent frugality, which is a duety of the eight Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, moſt requiſite for the diſcreet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing both of plentifull and poore E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, and neceſſary to bee obſerued by ſuch as intend an intire obedience vnto God, as well in one thing as in another; without which the royalty of <hi>Salomon,</hi> could not haue conſiſted for all his riches.</p>
               <p>I know that as in full bodies euacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may bee not hurtfull: yet, if a man
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14817:44"/> ſhould be purged and let blood euery ſix moneths, without faile, for many yeares together, it would not onely weaken, but at laſt conſume him: So in plentifull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates to bee ſometimes ſtraitned and put vpon difficulties, may be of vſe to make the rich more cautelous for themſelues, and more ſenſible of poore mens wants. Yet if the richeſt ſhould be put to do his homage to the Vſurer euery ſix moneths after eight or ten in the hundreth, <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> for many yeares together, and for great ſummes, without failing or excuſe, it would waſt by degrees the greateſt wealth that is, till it were exhauſted and vtterly brought to nought.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reges Parthos non poteſt quiſquam ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sen. Epiſt.</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>ſine munere;</hi> No man might ſalute the Parthian Kings without a preſent. A man may not ſalute an Vſurer <hi>gratis,</hi> nor looke him in the face (which yet muſt bee done at times prefixed) without the tribute of intereſt in his hand. Yet is he not molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied at all by this: but, as the Philiſtimes, when they had put out <hi>Samſons</hi> eyes, <note place="margin">Iudg. 16. 21</note> made him grinde in the Mil: ſo, when bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers are blinded with a thicke miſt of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:14817:44"/> probabilities to inſtifie their owne parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular caſe, then the Vſurer makes them grinde in his Mill. All the profit they can make by induſtry or skil, perhaps by rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tenants, and robbing the Church, is added to his heape: and when they haue compaſſed the circle from yeare to yeare; they are iuſt where they were at firſt. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the yeelding of the intereſt all the while, yet the debt remaines intire. In payment whereof, if any default bee made, then forfeitures and ſuites at law, and coſts &amp; damages; then executions vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on body, goods, lands, &amp; impriſonments, till the vtmoſt farthing be paied, do enſue.</p>
               <p>Thus the Borrowers thrift is ſpent, their ſubſtance is dilapidated, their wiues and children are impoueriſhed, &amp; themſelues wearied with labouring for the winde; which how it ſtands with that diſcreet frugality which God requireth in his moſt righteous Law, and without which no State can ſtedfaſtly hold out: let them whom it concernes examine, for ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne conſciences, and not goe on with ſecurity where there is certainty of danger.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:14817:45"/>
               <p> This foundation being now laid, that the borrower is not alwaies ſo innocent as is ſuppoſed, let vs hear what men indebted, and not reſolued to ſeeke their freedome, will ſay further for themſelues.</p>
               <p>Debt is chiefly by borrowing or buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Allegat. </seg>2</label> vpon time; I borrowed, ſaith the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of debt, but I purchaſed with it, and a great penniworth I had at the hands of a young Prodigall, who ſcatters more in a yeare, then he will gather in an age: him I obſerued and humoured, I furniſhed him with ſupply for all exceſſe of ryot, till I found an opportunity to lay out all my ſtocke, and great ſummes beſides out of the Vſurers treaſury. <hi>Torua leaena Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Virg. Ecl.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſequitur, lupus ipſe capellam;</hi> Thou art as a rauening Wolfe to the wanton vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrift, til the grimme Vſurer deuoure you both. But was this well done of thee to worke vpon the ignorance, or neceſſity, or wilfulneſſe, of a raw and vnexperien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Waſter, and to builde thy riſing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ruine? Shall any man be eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <note place="margin">Prou. 12. 3.</note> by wickednes? Was it well done, by crafty inſinuation to circumvent thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Is not God an auenger of all ſuch? <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4. 6.</note>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:14817:45"/> What elſe is this, but, <hi>Crimen ſtellionatus;</hi> the very ſinne of couſenage? Yet for all thy cunning, and buying at an vnderua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, do but add to the price, that which is paid for the loane, and in ſeuen yeares it will prooue very deare, vnleſſe thou helpe thy ſelfe in making the poore a prey; and ſo, <hi>Lucrum tuum,</hi> ſhall be, <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num publicum;</hi> Thy priuate gaine ſhall be a publike loſſe: as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> obſerueth; <hi>Officiorum, Lib.</hi> 3. And indeed in moſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it ſo falls out to bee, euen in thoſe which ſeeme moſt tollerable. A skilfull Tradeſman (for example) lackes a ſtocke; another that wanteth skill hath money ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by him, to no vſe nor profit; here, by the paſſage of an vſurious contract, the money of the wealthie is accommodated to the induſtry of the skilfull, and ſo both become gayners. And may they not both become looſers, God denying his bleſſing to vnſanctified meanes? Is not euery vniuſt gaine a true loſſe? Though gain in the Coffer, yet wrack in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: But of this they are willing not to be ſenſible. Admit them both gainers in ſundry returnes, yet may not the poore
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14817:46"/> Buyer, (honeſter then them both) be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by this occaſion, to pay a higher rate for commodities, without which mans life is not ſuſtained. And where this practiſe is generall, (Vſury being the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching ſinne of the age as Poligamie ſometimes was) may it not turne to the publike detriment of Buyers and Borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, when the Seller muſt proportion the price, as well to the aduantage of the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, as to the induſtry of ſuch as are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, and the worth of the thing? May not this raiſe iuſt cries and complaints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them both in the Court of heauen? Why doth <note n="*" place="margin">Ierem. 15 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieremy</hi> cleere himſelfe both of lending vpon vſury, and of borrowing vpon vſury, if there may not in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be matter of exception againſt them both?</p>
               <p>Another alledgeth for his continuance <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Allegat. </seg>3</label> in debt, that, Hee doth it to preſerue his ancient Inheritance, which is a good thing and a iuſt: one would be loath to be the man, in whoſe perſon and time, the ſplendour of a family ſhould be eclipſed. It was the honour of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> that hee could ſay of <hi>Rome; Accepi lateritiam, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:14817:46"/> 
                  <hi>marmoream;</hi> I receiued it of Bricke, I left it of Marble. But, as it is better in a Gangrene to cut off one member, then by ſuffring it to fret from part to part, to loſe the whole: ſo, when great and grieuous debts conſume a mans reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, it's better by ſelling part of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, though ancient, to cleare the State, then by ſuffering this Gangrene to ouerſpread the whole, at laſt to loſe all. Antiquity will not pay the rent of Vſury: And a debt continued til it be ancient, wil conſume the moſt ancient both inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and reputation.</p>
               <p>I continue in debt, will another ſay, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Allegat. </seg>4</label> that my trading be not diminiſhed: it's great dealing that brings in great gaining: ſo then, as one notes; <hi>Lucrum eſt eſca, ſed fraus eſt laqueus, ſic attende eſcam, vt vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as &amp; laqueum;</hi> Gaine is the bayte, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit is the ſnare; ſo looke at the baite, that thou diſcerne alſo the ſnare. But com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in trading men light vpon the ſnare, committing fraud induſtriouſly with both their hands, who yet could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer catch the baite, the gaine which did allure them. Nor is it any maruell, for in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:14817:47"/> debt continued, there is certainty of loſſe, but in great trading, aboue a mans abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, no certainty of gaine, nor aſſurance of Gods bleſſing, when men take too much vpon them, and will be rich in all haſte, againſt the rule of <note n="*" place="margin">Prou. 20. 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Salomon,</hi> who teacheth; that, An inheritance haſtily got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſhall not prooue happy in the latter end.</p>
               <p>Another imputes his debt vnto great <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Allegat. </seg>5</label> houſe-keeping, and maintaining himſelfe according to his birth and ranke. This is a meere friuolous pretence; for, when God cuts vs ſhort in point of ability, ſhould not we abridge our ſelues in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of expence? muſt wee not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to cut our Coat according to our cloath? It is the quarrell of God againſt <note place="margin">Eſay 22. 12 13, 14.</note> the Iewes, that when hee called to lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and mourning, to baldneſſe and ſackcloth; behold ioy and gladneſſe, ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Oxen and killing of Sheepe, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of fleſh and drinking of wine; <hi>As I liue,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>this iniquity ſhall not be purged till yee die.</hi> When God, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſhing a mans houſe, calls from ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity, to a moderate ſtint, &amp; a ſtrickter
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14817:47"/> courſe, ſhall wee goe on in lauiſhing and in ſpending exceſſiuely aboue our meanes? And ſhall not God abridge vs and daily cut vs ſhort, till he haue caſt vs vpon extreamities? <hi>Qui iniuſte ſe ordinat</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. Honor epiſt.</hi> 120.</note> 
                  <hi>in peccatis, iuſte ordinatur in paenis;</hi> He that carries himſelfe vniuſtly in ſinning, ſhall bee ordered iuſtly in the puniſhment of ſinne.</p>
               <p>Others lay their debt vpon magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Allegat. </seg>6</label> of building, and furniture, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deuices and curioſities, and thinke it well beſtowed, becauſe they haue not ſpent it in eating and drinking. This kinde of delight, though very coſtly, is yet more permanent then thoſe which periſh ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, in the vſe; and of theſe it is ſaid; <hi>Haec ſunt quae faciunt inuitos mori;</hi> Theſe are the things which make men vnwilling to die; which ſhould make vs, whoſe life ought to be a meditation of death, leſſe willing to ſet our hearts vpon them, or to caſt our ſelues for them vpon the miſeries of debt. For mine owne part, I ſee no warrant for vndoing our ſelues vpon any appetite or humour of this kinde. If a man will bee ſumptuous in the ſatisfying
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14817:48"/> of any luſt whatſoeuer, the reuennues of an Empire will not keepe him out of debt.</p>
               <p>Others lay their debt vpon preferment <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Allega∣tion. </seg>7</label> of children in Offices, Mariages, Honors or the like: to whom I ſay, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an education in the ſeruice and feare of God, and ſupply of things neceſſarie for the preſent and time to come as God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables vs, and imploiment in ſuch vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as may yeeld a maintenance to the induſtrious, that they bee not caſt vpon the curteſies of a mercileſſe world, is the dutie and taske of Parents. The vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment affectation of ſuperfluities of wealth and eminency of honour, may be a ſtraine of pride and couetouſnes in vs, how euer God allots them in his prouidence to ſome. Beſides it is prepoſterous to put our ſelues in debt for the aduancement of one or many, the burden whereof muſt final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fall vpon him that ſhall inherit as well our debt as our ſtate.</p>
               <p>It is laſtly pleaded that the very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Allega∣tion. </seg>8</label> of things neceſſarie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, euen in a ſlender maner and meaſure is the cauſe of debt to ſome, theſe only of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14817:48"/> all the reſt are to bee pitied and excuſed; for <hi>vltra poſſe non eſt eſſe,</hi> men cannot do more then they can. If thoſe men pay their debts ſo farre as they are able, and keepe out of debt ſo farre as to them is poſſible, and craue not only patience and forbearance till they can make ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but remiſſion of the debt if their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie faile them vtterly; then they obſerue the precept of owing no man any thing, ſo farre as in them lyeth. Which that we may doe, it remaineth in the next place for eſchewing the inconueniences inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to a ſtate clogged with debt, to ſhew by what means and courſes debt may and ought to be auoided.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10. <hi>Directions for auoiding of Debt that it breake not vpon our estate.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS it is eaſier to keep out then to caſt out an enemy, ſo it is eaſier to keep debt out of our ſtate, then to remoue it hauing entred. The firſt and faireſt way to auoide debt that it breake not in vpon vs,
<gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:14817:49"/> and pouertie is not ſought vnto; it is the Lord that maketh poore and that maketh rich, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 7. There is a curſe vpon idleneſſe though men be rich, as in <hi>Sodom;</hi> vpon negligence and ſecuritie, as in the men of <hi>Laiſh, Iudges</hi> 18, 27. A curſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnlawfull practiſes though men be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious, as in <hi>Iehoiachim,</hi> whom God would not bleſſe though he vſed all inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of heart and hand to get riches, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> 22. Yea, there may be a curſe vpon the laborious, euen in lawfull things, if God be not firſt and chiefly ſought and ſerued by ſuch as profeſs religion, as <hi>Hag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gay</hi> 1. vpon the children of the Captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for building their owne houſes at their returne to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and neglecting the Lords houſe; for this cauſe they ſowed much, but reaped little; they did eate, and were not ſatisfied; they did drinke, and were not filled; they were clothed, but not warmed; they earned wages, but were not enriched. Yet at laſt, when they fell ſeriouſly to the worke of God, then hee returned graciouſly with his bleſſing vpon them. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. 19. The way then to auoid both debt, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14817:49"/> other conſuming miſeries, is faithfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry in a lawfull calling, which God vouchſafeth to crowne with his bleſſing, where the ſeruice is chiefly entended and done vnto him.</p>
               <p>Men of great eſtate and means are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten indebted, <hi>Vſque ad ſtuporem,</hi> euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to aſtoniſhment; for, where ſhould there be water, if not in the riuers? will you ſeeke it in ditches, which haue no ſpring to feed them? Where ſhould there bee plenty, if not among men of great poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions and reuennues? will you ſeeke it among thoſe who haue no ſuch ſtanding helpes to yeeld them ſupply? Yet, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times theſe men of great poſſeſſions, are full of nothing elſe but debt; and why ſo? Gods iudgment is vpon them, either for an idle, or an vnprofitable life; or, for actiuity and forwardneſſe in vanities and voluptuouſneſſe; or, for a heauy and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall hand in ſacriledge and oppreſſions; or, for neglecting the worke and ſeruice of God, when they will not miſſe a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute in aduancing their owne. But this they will not ſee, leſt they ſhould turne to him that ſtriketh: <note n="*" place="margin">Eſay 42. 25</note> 
                  <hi>God powred vpon Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:14817:50"/> 
                  <hi>the fury of his anger, and the ſtrength of battell, and it hath ſet him on fire round about, yet he knew not; and it burned him vp, yet he conſidered not:</hi> That is, he tooke no notice that this was Gods iudgment, and that his ſinne had deſerued it: ſo is it with theſe men, they ſee themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, but will not be brought to lay thoſe ſinnes diſtinctly to heart, for which they ſuffer and are conſumed.</p>
               <p>A ſecond way for the auoiding of debt is, diſcreet and honeſt thriftineſſe: <hi>Vecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal magnum parſimonia;</hi> Frugality is a great reuennue: the great ſaueurs are the rich men: hee that hauing gotten great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of wealth, by induſtry or patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, will ſpend exceſſiuely &amp; ryotuſly aboue his meanes, though hee bee rich, will quickly come to pouerty; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Prodigalls are commonly termed, <hi>Decoctores, Heluones, Gurgites,</hi> Spead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts, vnſatiable waſters, and deuourers; ſuch men wil neuer keep out of debt. It is noted of the Roman Common-wealth, that it periſhed and flouriſhed by thrifti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vnthriftineſſe: vnder the <hi>Bruti,</hi> the <hi>Fabritij,</hi> the <hi>Cincinnati,</hi> the <hi>Scipioes,</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:14817:50"/> frugall and moderate men, contemners of voluptuouſneſſe, it was moſt flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing; but, <hi>Abundantes voluptates diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderium</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Liuius lib.</hi> 1</note> 
                  <hi>per luxum &amp; libidinem, pereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di perdendique omnia invexêre;</hi> Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities of pleaſures brought in a deſire of ſpilling and ſpoiling all by luxurie and wantonneſſe, and then the State declined from the former eminencie of brightneſs; <note n="*" place="margin">Prou. 21. 27</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that loueth paſtime ſhall bee a poore man, and he that loueth wine and oyle ſhall not be rich:</hi> Voluptuouſneſſe &amp; vnthrifti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe will make a rich man poore, and a poore man penurious.</p>
               <p>This makes the Prodigall hang in the Mercers booke for his clothes, in the Taylors note for making, in the Butchers ſcore for his meate, and in his ſeruants debt for wages; and when thus many hands come to rifle one, they will quickly make an empty purſe. Yet let all theſe <note place="margin">Prou. 27. 22.</note> hands bray the vnthrift as wheat is braied in a morter with a peſtill, and his folly will not depart from him till it bee too late to ſpare when all is ſpent. As <hi>Adams</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 23. 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> intemperance in not abſtaining from the forbidden fruit did caſt him out of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14817:51"/> into a vale of teares, ſo riotous waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes in any kind, be it in meate, drinke, apparell, building, gaming or any other courſe of voluptuouſnes, is able to caſt a man out of plenty into penury, and out of a free and comfortable eſtate into debt and danger.</p>
               <p>A third way to auoid debt, is a ſeuere watch ouer our word and promiſe. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is debt, and muſt bee performed though to our hindrance. Faithfulneſſe in promiſes is the bond of humane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts; <hi>Fides inde dicta, quia fit quod dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> So called Fidelity, becauſe that which is ſaid is fulfilled. Circumſpect promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are of vſe I know to aſſure true mens words, to ſecure good mens hopes, to encourage induſtry, and make it liuely in well-doing; but then wee muſt beware wee bee not like <hi>Antigonus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>That will giue;</hi> ignominiouſly ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe forward in promiſing, but ſlacke in performing. Promiſes are as vowes, much better neuer made, then not made good: <hi>Facile ex amico inimicum facies cui pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hier. ad Celantiam.</note> 
                  <hi>non reddas;</hi> One may eaſily make of a friend a foe, to whom he keepes not
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14817:51"/> promiſes: yet what man almoſt is there of any competent ſtate, ſo cautelous and wary that is not ſometimes ſnared in his words, &amp; ouertaken with vnaduiſed ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhippe. Yet <hi>Salomon</hi> tells vs; that, He <note place="margin">Prou. 11 15</note> is vtterly quaſht in peeces that is ſurety for a Stranger: It is the rocke on which many make ſhipwracke of credite and: <hi>Sponſioni non deeſt iactura;</hi> Stipula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not without loſſe accompanying: it was the <hi>Symbolum,</hi> or memorable word of <hi>Chilo</hi> the Lacedemonian; <hi>Sponde, noxa praſto eſt:</hi> Paſſe thy promiſe, and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with enſues ſome hurt, ſaid a greater then hee. I know we ſhould <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 6. 2.</note> beare one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers burthen, and ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt, euen of charity; but to beare ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers burden till I ſinke vnder mine own, is no charity but folly; and to pull ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out till my ſelfe ſticke faſt, is no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion but deſtruction both to mee and mine: now, hee that promiſeth for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more then hee can performe, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ſuerty for another in more then he makes account to pay (if the principall debtor fayle) he is ſnared in his words, he <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 1, 2</note> is taken in the words of his owne mouth,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14817:52"/> nor dare I in all caſes excuſe his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, hee that will auoid the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of debt, muſt reſerue ſomething in ſtore againſt caſuall euents; I ſpeake not of publike iudgments, as war or famine, wherewith God viſits a Nation in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which are much more preuented or mitigated by repentance and prayer, then by any ciuill policy, but of priuate caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties, daily incident vpon the perſons or ſtates of men; in regard whereof, a man deſirous to liue out of debt, muſt reſolue to ſpend within his compaſſe, that he may haue ſomewhat more in readineſſe then from hand to mouth. What if ſickneſſe come, and make one the Lords priſoner, and binde his hands from diſpenſing his owne affaires? What is more ordinary? <hi>Da mihi corpus quod nunquam languerit,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anos lib</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>aut quod poſt languorem perpetua ſanitate ſecurum ſit;</hi> Shew me the body that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer languiſhed, or that is ſecure after ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe recouered. So long as corporall diſeaſes are ſpirituall remedies, God will hereby draw vs to the Phyſitian of our ſoules. Suppoſe loſſes come in the houſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14817:52"/> or in the field, <hi>Spem mentita ſeges, bos eſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Horat. epist. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 7</note> 
                  <hi>enectus arando;</hi> The crop anſwers not the coſt, or the expectation, the cattell are kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with working, or the like, no man hath a perpetuall gale of proſperity. <hi>Deus fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitatibus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. in Mat. Serm.</hi> 29.</note> 
                  <hi>terrenis amaritudines miſcet, vt alia quaeratur faelicitas, cuius dulcedo non eſt fallax;</hi> God mingleth bitterneſſe with earthly proſperity, that another hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe may be ſought, whoſe ſweetneſſe is not fallacious.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe Suites at Law come, which to ſome are ineuitable, for neceſſary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of innocency and patrimony, and yet are alwaies coſtly, whether one winne or loſe the thing in queſtion; and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous for breeding anger, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. ep.</hi> 87.</note> which cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts the heart as vinegar doth the veſſell wherein it doth continue. Suppoſe a mans charge be multiplied and encreaſed by number of children, poore, friends, ſtrangers, by frequent penſions and ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the Church or Common-wealth; ſuppoſe any of theſe, or many of theſe doe fall vpon a man that is not prouided before hand for them, hee cannot chuſe but runne in debt, he muſt borrow where
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14817:53"/> he can; and lending vpon any tollerable termes is in a manner out of date. Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man therfore ſo husband the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of thriuing and plenty, as wiſe-men doe of Vintage and Harueſt againſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der times enſuing, leſt the ſtorme ariſing from the mutability and viciſſitude of earthly tranſitory things, ouerwhelm him with debt, as the whirle-winde doth the vnwary Traueller vpon the Alpes with ſnow.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, there are baites to catch the moſt thriuing &amp; circumſpect men in the ſnares of debt; Ouer-purchaſing, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertrading: and, which is a conſequence of theſe, vſurious contracts. Ouer-purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and Ouer-trading are delightfull burdens, if a man can bear them without ſtraining conſcience or credite, or, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hazarding the principall, to compaſſe the ouerpluſſe; yet, becauſe the ayming at ſuperfluities and exceſſes, is but the fruit of an inordinate appetite, it were better to reſtraine both our actions and affections, to that which wee are able to wield, then to runne ſo greedily vpon the world: <hi>Qui periculoſior est blandus, quam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auſt. Epiſt.</hi> 144.</note>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:14817:53"/> 
                  <hi>moleſtus;</hi> Which is more dangerous, when it flatters vs, then when it afflicts vs? When it allures vs to loue it, then when it compells vs to deſpiſe it: <hi>He that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>loueth the world, and the things of the world, the loue of the father is not in him.</hi> Why then ſhould wee ſo wilfully and ſo eagerly embrace the world? the moderate loue whereof, as it is an alienation from God, and from the comfortable refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhings by the light of his countenance: ſo, inſteed thereof, it caſts vs vpon the mercies of the cruell, the Vſurer I meane; <hi>Qui alienas negotiatur miſerias, &amp; lucrum ſuum alterius aduerſitatem facit;</hi> The V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, I ſay, whoſe trafficke and trade it is to make men miſerable, and to raiſe his gaine out of other mens aduerſitie, he is ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome, Quaſi manum ſuſcipiens</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom.</hi> 6. <hi>in Matth.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; in naufragium impellens;</hi> As a man ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one by the hand to pull out of the water, but kicking him backe againe to the ſhipwracke of his ſubſtance, and of himſelfe, which is a rude and a barbarous part in any, to hurt infallibly, whom he pretends to helpe. This is one of the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter potions which the world reacheth
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:14817:54"/> forth to Ouer-purchaſers, and Ouer-tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which they are forced to drinke to the very dregges, when they cannot bee content to walke within their compaſſe. As a man cannot touch pitch but bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed therewith: ſo hee cannot deale with Vſury without detriment, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> the firſt moment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10. <hi>Directions how to get out of Debt, if wee be already intangled.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT may be theſe directions, for auoiding Debt, come too late for many men, who haue hitherto erred, not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the danger; and haue run conſtantly in a courſe of multiplying Debts, euer ſince they were of age and diſcretion to procure credite by giuing ſecurity. So that they may ſay of Debt, as the Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet <hi>Quartilla</hi> did of her virginity; <hi>Iunone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Petron. Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr.</note> 
                  <hi>meam iratam habeam, ſi vnquam me mimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerim virginem fuiſſe;</hi> So let me haue the diſpleaſure of my <hi>Iuno,</hi> if euer I can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member my ſelfe a Virgin; The like may
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14817:54"/> many a man ſay of this; <hi>Mammona me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um iratum habeam;</hi> So let mee haue the diſpleaſure of my <hi>Mammon,</hi> if euer I can remember my ſelfe out of debt; but I was alwaies a borrower of little ſummes, when I could not ſpeed in greater.</p>
               <p>To theſe now I ſay, that if they be ſo hardened with cuſtome of owing, that they haue ſetled a reſolution to liue and dye in debt: then indeed my counſell ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of eſchewing debt, that they come not in, or of quitting themſelues, being in already, can do them little good. They will deſpiſe it as a barren and naked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of a man without experience, who makes no difference between a meere Scholler, and a man wholly exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in worldly affaires. Well, let them hold their courſe, if it will be no better, I leaue them to the Vſurer to bee braied in his morter; or to the office of Inſurance, to be ſtript of thouſands by the lumpe, while they are catching after ſcraps by the morſell.</p>
               <p>There are others alſo, whoſe caſe falls not within the compaſſe of my aduiſe, ſuch I meane, as are either deſperate
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:14817:55"/> Bankrupts profeſſedly; or, indeed and in truth, being indebted for great ſummes, are little worth, and haue no poſſibility to pay. For, as the <hi>Pſylli</hi> of <hi>Lybia,</hi> who had power to cure the byting of Serpents, by ſucking the venome out of the wounds, could not helpe <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Rom. Hiſt. lib.</hi> 51</note> 
                  <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> Queene of Aegypt, ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with Aſpes, or with a poyſoned Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, or Criſping-pin, becauſe the poyſon was diſperſed through all the veines, and had damped the vitall ſpirits, before they came: And, as Phyſitians vndertake not to worke a cure where the principall parts of the body are waſted away: ſo, where Debt hath run through euery part, and hath ſearched euery veine of a mans ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and as a poyſon hath fretted in true calculation both goods &amp; lands, it's paſt my skill to preſcribe any remedy, to get out, where there is no matter to work vpon. I can onely leaue ſuch to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God and men, as Phyſitians doe their Patients in deſperate diſeaſes. I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe my ſelfe to thoſe, who hauing ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left, are willing to improoue the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of their time and ſtate, in get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:14817:55"/> and keeping themſelues out of debt.</p>
               <p>The firſt direction for comming out of Debt, is that which <hi>Salomon</hi> giues for getting out of ſuertiſhip, <hi>Prou.</hi> 6. 3, 4, 5. Submit thy ſelfe, and entreat thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſolicite the Creditour, <hi>vt diem am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliet,</hi> to haue patience with thee, and to grant ſome reſpit: ſolicite the Debtor, for which thou art engaged, <hi>Vt fidem liberet,</hi> to cleare his fidelity by keeping promiſe: ſolicite thy friends to enterpoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to mediate for thee, to put to their helping hand. Giue thy ſelfe no reſt, nor ſleepe to thine eyes, till thou be deliuered as a Roe from the hand of the Hunter, or as a Bird from the Snare of the Fowler. Delay breeds danger, put it not off. If we muſt doe thus when we are engaged for others, how much more when the debt is our owne?</p>
               <p>All meanes muſt be vſed inſtantly, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunately, not to renue the bond from ſix moneths to ſix moneths, till many years be expired, that is a meditated con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in the ſnare, and an addition to the debt: as if a man in fetters &amp; chaines,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14817:56"/> ſhould entreat that one ten pound more, one todd more, one hundreth weight more might bee added to his Shack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, and laid vpon him. But all meanes muſt bee vſed by ſubmiſſion, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, by helpe of friends, ſatisfaction muſt bee giuen to the vttermoſt that the ſtate will beare, before it bee cleane waſted, that it may manifeſtly appeare, that wee are truly willing not to delude the world, nor to raiſe our ſelues a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune by defrauding others; but ſo farre as wee are able to giue contentment, and where power faileth, to craue remiſſion or reſpit, without further aggrauating the burden by intereſt. Nor muſt theſe ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous endeauours bee deferred, but as the <note n="*" place="margin">Eſay 51. 14</note> captiue haſteneth to bee looſed, that he dye not in the pit, and that his bread faile not, ſo muſt we quit our ſelues, that debt pine vs not in the pit. Say not; He is my friend, he will ſpare me, I need not feare, he will vſe no extreamity; for, if he be a free lender, he will not bee a long lender, he deſerueth currant &amp; ſpeedy paiment. If the Creditour be an Vſurer, then the debt is nothing mittigated, but doubled
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:14817:56"/> by continuance, though thou ſleepe thus indebted, yet thy conſuming diſeaſe ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not: this worme dyeth not till the debt be payed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui non eſt hodie: cras minus aptus erit;</hi> The longer in debt, the leſſe able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge it: the burden will encreaſe hower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and thy ability will be deminiſhed by the very edacity of debt. Follow then the Prophets counſell; <hi>Giue no ſleepe to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>thine eies, nor to thine eye-lids any ſlumber, till thou bee deliuered as a Deere out of the ſnare.</hi> I cannot but interpret the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Salomon,</hi> as an intimation of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, if it bee followed. I take it for a rule, that obedience to holy authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall counſells and precepts, is alwaies an aſſurance of good ſucceſſe to him that practiſeth the ſame, which hath made me importunate in vrging expedition. All things I know muſt haue a time, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueterate diſeaſes are not cured in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, onely bee impatient till thou finde the meanes, and reſtleſſe in the way of getting out of debt: which way I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eat out as a ſecond remedie.</p>
               <p>That contraries are cured by contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:14817:57"/> is often true, and certainly in this: <hi>Egreſſus malitiae, virtutis operatur ingreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, Ambroſe;</hi> The out going of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe works an entrance vnto good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If a man came in debt by intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, he muſt come out by ſobriety; if by ryot and voluptuouſneſſe, hee muſt binde himſelfe to a ſtricter and ſeuerer courſe. <hi>Legimus quoſdam</hi> (ſaies <hi>Hierome) morbo articulari &amp; podagrae humoribus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borantes, proſcriptione bonorum ad ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem menſam &amp; pauperes cibos redactos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ualuiſſe:</hi> Wee haue read of ſome, who being ſicke of the Gout through abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of humours, did recouer their health, being forced to a poore and ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der dyet by confiſcation of their goods. As extrauagant humours are cured by a ſparing dyet, which came by ryotouſneſs; ſo all other ſuperfluities are tempered by moderation. Hee therefore that ran in debt by any exceſſe, muſt come out by order, and a diſcreet method of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect mediocrity. If a man came in debt by ouer-purchaſing, he muſt be content to ſell; if by ouer-trading, hee muſt not ouerlay himſelfe with that burden, vnder
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:14817:57"/> which he hath ſunke already; if by ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe in apparell, if by curioſities in building: theſe ſuperfluous expences vpon our luſts muſt be cut off, Men muſt not imitate <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Athenaeus lib.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 8.</note> the magnificence of <hi>Lucul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> without the wealth of <hi>Lucullus;</hi> no, nor yet of <hi>Salomon,</hi> he liued in a golden, we in an iron age. Finally, if a man came in debt by idleneſſe, and ſloath, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſſe; hee muſt ſtruggle out by a contrary courſe of diligence and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie, and employment in well doing. A neceſſity lieth vpon him ſo to doe: for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man is bound to eate his own bread which he can neuer doe, that paies not his debts truly, but liues and ſpends vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans ſtocke and ſubſtance, taking the iniury vpon himſelfe, but leauing the iuſtice and mercie to another.</p>
               <p>But alas, may ſome man ſay (in preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of this aduice) how little can one mans induſtrie and frugality auaile, in the remouing and ouercomming of great and conſuming debts? theſe are aboue the power and reach of a man alreadie ſunke and decaied in his eſtate. To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; Firſt, that the diligence and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:14817:58"/> of ſome one man may be of great ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie in it ſelfe, for the accompliſhment of great matters, if God bee with him; <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 30. 27. 30.</note> as of <hi>Iacob</hi> in the ſeruice of <hi>Laban,</hi> whom God bleſſed for his ſake, and encreaſed his little into a multitude. So <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 40. to Chap. 48.</note> of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in <hi>Pharaohs.</hi> Alſo the diligence and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent frugality of one may bee of conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence in the example to many; as <note n="*" place="margin">Ruth chap. 2. &amp; 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Booz</hi> may be a patterne in this kind to all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: how did he follow the buſineſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? How were his eies on the Seruants, on the Reapers? euen on the gleaners? hee doth euen lodge in the mideſt of his husbandry.</p>
               <p>Secondly I anſwer, that diligence, thrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, temperance after a rude and vnru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly courſe, are not ſo much to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in themſelues, as in the bleſſing of God annexed vnto them, which can as well draw men out of debt, as adorne them with riches. If <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 15. 22.</note> the prodigall be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo needy, yet if the father will receiue him vpon his ſubmiſſion, the ragges will quickly bee changed into roabes. This changing alſo of the former miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors into a ſtate of reformation; of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluteneſſe
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14817:58"/> and luxury, into diligence and ſobriety, is an euidence and an exerciſe of true repentance; without which, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe nor deliuerance from the iudgments of God, which haue ceazed vpon vs, can be expected. Whereas vpon repentance and amendment, which implies an intire change of the minde, and of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and a liuely accommodating of our will to the worke, and of our beſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours to the accompliſhment of our iuſt deſires: deliverance in due time may be expected, as well from this of debt, as from any other iudgment of God. His hand that laid it on, can take it off againe, if he be ſought vnto by feruent praier and ſupplication, which I willingly propound as the next remedie and ſpeciall helpe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt debt.</p>
               <p>In thoſe things which are meerly ciuill, and are tranſacted by dexterity in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging worldly affaires, it is a hard thing to make men beleeue (ſo that induſtry and skil be vſed) that prayer is of any great conſequence for good or bad euents. This makes the Day-labourer, the Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, the Husbandman (for moſt part) fall
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14817:59"/> down-right to his worke, without any ſet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> inuocation of God, more then perhaps a <hi>Pater noſter</hi> inhaſt, or ſome other word of courſe, without in tention of the ſpirit. As they deale in other things, ſo likewiſe in this of debt; they are ſenſible of the burden, and capable of all politike dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, tending to their eaſe; but how praier and debt ſhould haue any relation, or the one giue furtherance to the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the other, they are not willing to conceiue. And hence it is, that being perplexed in this labyrinth of debt, they caſt away their confidence, nor ſeeking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny iſſue or helpe by praier; yet <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 4. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> hath taught in all things to make our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts knowne to God by praier and ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plication. If in all things, why not in debt? <note n="*" place="margin">2. Chro. 6. 29. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Salomon</hi> hath taught vs; that, When a man ſhall ſee his owne plague, and his owne diſeaſe, and ſhall make his moane accordingly, God ſhall heare him in heauen. Now they, who are for other things in a kinde of ſtupidity, yet acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge debt to bee their plague and vndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Why then vſe they not the remedy preſcribed by the wiſeſt? <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 50. 15.</note> God himſelfe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:14817:59"/> encouraging to call vpon him in the day of trouble, and they eſteeming this to be the vlcer of all their trouble? If the houſe cannot be builded, if the Citie can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be guarded without the Lord; if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be done by early riſing and late reſting, but onely ſo far as God puts to his helping hand, working in vs and for vs: why then is not hee entreated for his aſſiſtance, in this difficulty of debt, as well as in other things? When <hi>Amazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Chr. 25. 9</note> asked the man of God, who forbad him to take the Ephraimits into the battle againſt the Edomits, becauſe God was not with them, what then ſhould become of the hundreth talents, which he had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them for their helpe? cannot God, ſaid the Prophet, giue thee more then this? So ſay I to him that trembles at the inundation of debt vpon him; Cannot God, if he were ſought vnto, giue an iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue out of this? Cannot God, if the ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocke of thine iniquity, (which makes the ſeparation, and hinders good things from thee) were remoued, giue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen more then this? If it bee replied; That God worketh men out of debt, by
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:14817:60"/> meanes, which thou haſt neither in thy power, nor in thy view. To this I ſay, that prayer it ſelfe is a means, wherby all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther helps &amp; practiſes receiue their force, vertue, &amp; ſucceſſe, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> haue failed hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to for want of this. Faithfull praier puts a man vpon the cheerefull vſe of ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate meanes, and binds to ſuch pertinent courſes, and ſerious endeauours, as are moſt likely to remoue, or at leaſt to miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate this languiſhing conſumption of our eſtate. All our policies without this are but, <hi>Arena ſine calce,</hi> Sand without Lime. They will not hold together when wee haue moſt need of them, but like vntem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered morter, will fall aſunder. Let ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt praier be ioyned with frugality, skill, and diligence, and payment ſo far as our ability will extend; and then expect with comfort the end that God will giue.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe when all is done that is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted or deuiſed, that we cannot for all this ſatisfie the Creditour; yet this ſhewes a mans repentance for his former indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and his true deſire to make ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when hee ſeriouſly ſets himſelfe to make ſuch payment as to him is any way
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:14817:60"/> poſſible: which though it come ſhort of contenting the Creditour, may notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſerue to pacifie the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience of the Debtor, which will bee ſurely clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous where iuſtice is not done to a mans power, by yeelding euery man his owne.</p>
               <p>I know ſome cruell Lenders will bee bitter &amp; violent in exacting, which makes the clamours great of oppreſſed Borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5. yea, ſeceſſions of the poore, and ſeparations from the rich, as appeares in the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Liuius D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 2.</note> Roman ſtory, but no cry is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable, as of a tender conſcience, if debts and duties be not faithfully perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Let vs therefore not remaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted any thing to any man, but pay e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man his due, not out of conſtraint onely, but euen for conſcience ſake.</p>
               <p>I end with <hi>Aquinas</hi> his words vpon this place, <hi>It a plené omnibus omnia debita perſoluatis, vt nihil remaneat quod ſoluere debeatis;</hi> Pay all your debts ſo fully vnto all, that (ſo farre as is poſſible) nothing reſt behind which ought to be paid; the debt of loue onely excepted, which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes in the next place. Hitherto of civill and mixt debts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:14817:61"/>
               <head>CHAP. 12. <hi>Of the ſacred Debt of Loue, that we ought to loue one another, and why?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BVT that yee loue one another.]</hi> As is the Obligation, ſuch is the Debt: ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill obligations ceaſe when the pecuniary debt is paid, but the bond of loue among Chriſtians is perpetuall; ſo that as wee ſay of thankes in caſe of benefits receiued, <hi>Gratiae agendae &amp; habendae;</hi> Thankes muſt be giuen and held as ſtill due: ſo of loue it is; <hi>Debitum ſemper reddendum &amp; ſemper habendum;</hi> A debt which alwaies is to be paid, and yet alwaies continues payable; <hi>I am</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) a debtor, both to the Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. L 14</note> 
                  <hi>and Barbarian, both to the wiſe and to the vnwiſe;</hi> hee meanes the debt of loue and of ſeruice. The inſtruction is this; That Loue and Charity is a due debt, perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be performed by one Chriſtian to another; <hi>Let brotherly loue continue, Heb.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe, I am the Lord, Leuit.</hi> 19. 18. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14817:61"/> let vs loue one another; for loue is of God, and euery one that loueth is born of God and knoweth God. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 7. <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 13. 34</note> 
                  <hi>A new Commandement giue I vnto you, that yee loue one another.</hi> How a new com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandent? <hi>Auſtine</hi> anſweres, <hi>quia exuto veteri induit nos nouum hominem</hi> Becauſe the old man being put off, it puts on vs the new man. Whereunto I adde this, that when the Scribes and Phariſes by falſe gloſſes and corrupt interpretations had put it out of date; <note n="*" place="margin">Mat 5. 43, 44, 45, 46, &amp;c.</note> Chriſt reſtored it by a true interpretation, and reuiued and illuſtrated it by his owne practiſe and example: as <hi>Paul</hi> alſo doth obſerue, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Walke in loue as Christ hath loued vs,</hi> and <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 9. <hi>This I pray that your loue may abound more and more in knowledge, and in all iudgement.</hi> To walke in loue intendeth a proceeding and going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward till wee come to an eminencie, and this we ſhould indeuour.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> Firſt, becauſe it is a good thing and a pleaſant, <note place="margin">Pſal. 133. 1.</note> that brethren, ſhould dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in vnitie and amitie. Some things are pleaſant that are not good, as vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gaines to a couetous man. <note n="*" place="margin">2. Pet 2. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Balaam</hi>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:14817:62"/> loues the wages of iniquitie to his hurt: ſome things are good that are nor plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, as to ſuffer affliction, ſo <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 11. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> did with the people of God: But the loue of the brethren is both good and pleaſant: Good, becauſe agreeable to Gods will: Pleaſant, becauſe comfortable to the heart of man to inioy the ſocietie and communion of Saints: both good and pleaſant, <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 133. 3.</note> becauſe God hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his bleſſing to reſt vpon the vnitie of brethren in that which is good.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt hath loued vs being his <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 5. 2. 10.</note> enemies; therefore we ought to loue one another: If Chriſt haue taught vs this, not only by precept, but alſo by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and by illuſtration of the precept in his owne perſon, ſhould we not herein conforme our ſelues vnto him? Should not euerie one accommodate himſelfe to that, which is the proper end and vſe of his calling? Should not the Shepheard feed his flocke, the Pilot at Sea guide his Ship, the Captaine in warre exerciſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie diſcipline? Should not the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man keepe his watch? Now brotherly loue is as proper and peculiar to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:14817:62"/> as any of theſe ſeruices to the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of them. By this ſhall all men know, that ye are my diſciples, if ye loue one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13. 35.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, many excellent things are ſpoken of loue: it is <note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 1. 5.</note> the end and ſcope of the Lawe; <hi>Vt eſt in medicina ſanitas,</hi> as health is the end of Phyſicke. It is the ſumme of the Lawe ſayth Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 40. Where hee ſpeakes of the loue of God, and of the loue of man iointly: In which ſenſe it is noted to bee a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent vertue required in euery com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. It is the <note n="*" place="margin">Col. 3. 14.</note> bond of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>quo omnia hominum inter ſe officia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentur &amp; coherent,</hi> wherein all the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which paſſe betweene men are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and combined. As faith is the bond of our vnion with Chriſt, ſo is loue of our communion with our brethren, the members of Chriſt, in which two conſiſts the perfection of the myſticall bodie. It is called here the fulfilling of the Lawe, both in this verſe and in the tenth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, <hi>qui diligit, non vnum aliquod prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum obijt, ſed in genere praeſtitit quod lex iubet,</hi> he that loueth, obſerueth not ſome
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14817:63"/> one precept, but performeth in generall what the Law inioineth, but of this in the next place.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Fourthly, where loue is not, the life of man is like a perpetuall tempeſt, here ruſhing, and there bluſtering, here bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and there bearing downe all before it; without this wee ſtill doe liue in the gall of bitterneſſe and bond of iniquitie: where this failes, miſchief comes in place thereof; diſſentions, diſcords and ſuch curſes as accompany them. <hi>Non eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſent</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprian. Ep.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>fratribus haec mala, ſi in vnum fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitas fuiſſet animata.</hi> Such euills had not befallen the brethren, if the brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood had held together in one mind. Let vs therefore nouriſh this precious charity in our hearts, in obedience and true conformity vnto Chriſt; as alſo for the worthineſſe of the grace it ſelfe, and for our owne refreſhing and conſolation in our pilgrimage here on earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:14817:63"/>
               <head>CHAP. 13. <hi>Of the diuerſities of loue, and of the nature of Chriſtian religious loue, towards one another.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BVT that ye loue one another.]</hi> We haue a rule euen in moral diſcipline that the prayſe of vertue conſiſteth in action. This is as true of loue as of any other whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, <note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 13.</note> in this preferred before faith and hope, not ſimply, but becauſe it is diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue of it ſelfe to the vſe of others, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as theſe are confined to the perſon of the beleeuer. Wee haue alſo another rule that whatſoeuer wee would that men ſhould doe vnto vs, euen ſo ſhould we do to them; for this is the Law and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 12. But wee deſire that men ſhould loue vs, and accommodate themſelues to our ſeruice; therefore it is a naturall and a perpetuall debt to do the like vnto them.</p>
               <p>Now that loue may be diffuſiue of it ſelfe in precious ſtreams, and operatiue with approbation of God and of man:
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:14817:64"/> let vs chooſe out among the ſeuerall kinds of loue, 1. the moſt excellent in nature, 2. the beſt eſteem'd in quality, 3. the moſt beneficial in the operations &amp; fruits of it.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, wee muſt obſerue that there are diuerſe kinds of loue; as naturall affection whereby wee loue our Parents, Children, and Kindred. Hee that hath not this is worſe then brutiſh: euen beaſts cheriſh and ſuckle their young ones. This though a Chriſtian cannot want, yet a reprobate may haue. There is a ciuil loue, the obligation whereof is domeſticall or politicall ſocietie. Meere naturall men yeeld this for mutuall commodity and conſolation. There is a morall loue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in an exact compenſation of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with affection, of benefite with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, which falls ſhort indeed of that loue which here we ſeeke, as our Sauiour ſhewes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 46. 47. It may be in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate men, yet it is a great furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to the producing and preſeruing of the charity, whereof we ſpeake. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <note place="margin">Greg. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zian.</note> Nothing ſo auaileable vnto loue, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of affection: which is expreſſed
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:14817:64"/> by mutuall offices, <hi>Vis vt ameris, ama;</hi> Wilt thou be beloued, then do thou loue.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, there is a chriſtian religious loue, which is a ſanctified affection, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our hearts are ioyned either to our brethren in the faith, in contemplation of Gods image in them, ſhining in an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of Graces; or in reſpect of the common hope of our calling, declared by outward profeſſion; or elſe whereby we wiſh and doe good to our enemies, in obedience to him who hath commanded vs ſo to doe.</p>
               <p>There is not any kinde of theſe loues aboue mentioned, but it is a debt; and ſo is this chriſtian religious loue alſo, and muſt be duely paied. Firſt, in reſpect of the communion of Saints: there is one body, one ſpirit, one hope of our calling, one lord, one faith, one baptiſme, one God and father of all, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 4, 5, 6. If a <note n="*" place="margin">Eccle. 4. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> three-fold cord bee not eaſily broken, how much leſſe this of loue in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of inuincible obligations? It muſt alſo be paied as an homage to God, who will take no notice of our loue to him, vnleſſe we loue our neighbour; <hi>Thou</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:14817:65"/> 
                  <hi>ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe, I am the Lord, Leuit.</hi> 19. 18. as alſo 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4. 20. <hi>Hee that ſaith hee loueth God and hateth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is a lyar. Who ſo loueth not his brother whom he hath ſeene, how can hee loue God whom bee hath not ſeene?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, it muſt bee paid, in regard of mutuall offices and duties, as of tender affections and earneſt prayers for one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; the intercourſe whereof cannot be ſtopped among Chriſtians. <hi>Maior eſt fraternitas Christi, quàm ſanguinis;</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood in Chriſt is ſtronger then in blood. If kinne will creepe where it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not goe, chriſtian charity cannot chuſe but be diffuſiue of it ſelfe, from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the loweſt. <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 133. 2. 3.</note> As the precious oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the head of <hi>Aaron</hi> to his beard, and to the skirts of his garment: as the dew of <hi>Hermon</hi> vpon the hill of <hi>Zion;</hi> ſo this loue imparts it ſelfe by a co-operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods ſpirit, to the comfort and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of high and low, pertaining to the couenant.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, as in ciuill debts, ſo alſo in ſacred, the paiment muſt be currant. It is not the loue of brethren in euill, bee it
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:14817:65"/> neuer ſo ſtrong that will ſerue the turne; ſuch concord is a conſpiracy, as in <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 34, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Sime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Leui,</hi> in the outrage vpon the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemites. It is not the doting of <note n="*" place="margin">Iudg. 16. 4. &amp;c. Num. 25. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Samſon</hi> vpon <hi>Dalilah,</hi> or of <hi>Zimry</hi> vpon <hi>Cosby,</hi> be the men neuer ſo great, that will ſerue the turne; this is but carnall luſt. The currant loue which beares the ſtampe of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie, muſt bee deriued <note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 1. 5.</note> from a pure heart, a good conſcience, &amp; an vnfaigned faith; this is the right myne out of which it muſt be taken. And in this reſpect the chriſtian loue doth as much ſurmount all carnall loues, as gold or ſiluer doth cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or lead; which makes mee wonder, why we ſhould bee ſo ambitious of the friendſhip and countenance of men no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly ſinfull, ſeeing how much ſoeuer they are beloued of vs, yet they can but giue vs droſſe for gold, chaffe for wheat. True chriſtian loue indeed, as it is a noble heroicall grace, ſo can it not proceed but from a ſanctified originall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:14817:66"/>
               <head>CHAP. 14. <hi>The qualities of religious Loue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS is the nature of religious Loue, ſo are the qualities holy and heauenly. Theſe are three; Patience, Conſtancy, and Feruency: Loue is patient; Charity ſuffereth long, and is kinde; it is not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily prouoked, it beareth all things, it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth all things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 4, 5. 7. The Iſraelits depoſe <hi>Samuel</hi> from his gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as great an indignity as could bee deuiſed; yet, <hi>God forbid</hi> (ſaid hee) <hi>that I ſhould ceaſe to pray for you, or to ſhew you the right way,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. This was the patience of his loue, to recompence good for euill. <hi>Saul</hi> perſecutes <hi>Dauid</hi> bitterly; <note place="margin">1. Sam. 24. 5 &amp; 26. 11. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> hauing his life in his power twice, takes not the opportunity of priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, but diſmiſſeth him ſafe; this was the patience of his loue to the Lords an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed; <note n="ȣ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg. hom</hi> 7 <hi>in Ezech.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Patientia vera eſt, quae ipſum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat quem portat;</hi> It is true patience to loue him whoſe weight we feele. Thus the nurſe beares the vnquietneſſe of her
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:14817:66"/> child, that breakes her ſleepe: the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ignorance and wilfulneſſe of the oppoſite: the husband and the wife ſuffer the infirmities of each other without grudging or repyning, becauſe there is true loue in the fleſh, and in the Lord. As is the meaſure of Loue, ſo of Patience: much loue, much patience. Loue is ſtrong as death, being ſupported with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience. Whereupon alſo doth depend the next property which is Conſtancy.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle hauing ſaid, that <hi>Charity</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aquin. in hunc locum</note> 
                  <hi>beareth all, and endureth all things;</hi> infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the next words; <hi>Charity neuer fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 8. <hi>Charitas in diligendo non deficit, ſed proficit;</hi> Charity in louing goes not backward but forward; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in the <hi>Philippians,</hi> whoſe loue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded more and more. The loue of <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Naomi,</hi> makes her cleaue vnto her conſtantly, though ſhee had perſwaſions, and example, and diſcouragements to the contrary, yet the reſolution was; That nought but death ſhould make a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <note place="margin">Ruth 1. 16 17.</note> The like ſtedfaſtneſſe is in the loue of <hi>Paul</hi> towards the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> though the more he loued them, the leſſe he was
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:14817:67"/> beloued, <hi>Yet will I ſpend most willingly</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and will bee ſpent for your ſakes,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 15.</p>
               <p>True loue is not apprehenſiue of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor alienated vpon ſleight occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, though the ſeruices of loue bee ſometimes coſtly, as in relieuing the poore: and the labour of loue ſometimes painfull, as of <note n="*" place="margin">Ierem. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>Ebedmelecke</hi> in drawing <hi>Ieremy</hi> out of the dungeon of <hi>Malchiah,</hi> hazarding thereby the diſpleaſure of Prince and State. Yet loue, armed with conſtancy, perſiſteth in good purpoſes; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all difficulties &amp; oppoſitions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer; yea, when many other eminent gifts doe ceaſe, yet ſhall loue continue, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 8. 9.</p>
               <p>The third quality of this loue is Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uency. <hi>Aboue all things haue feruent loue among your ſelues,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 8. This ſets an edge on loue, it keepes it from languiſhing, it ſuffers not ſo gracious an affection to ſettle vpon the lees of ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſhneſſe, but will quicken it as a taske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter, exacting daily the ſeruice of the day, it will make vs reſtleſſe til ſome good be done, and ſenſible in caſe we faile: as
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14817:67"/> is noted of <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hieron. in Epiſt. ad Gal. cap.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Titus</hi> the Emperour, when he had not done ſome memorable good, he would lament the loſſe of ſuch a day. Feruency will make vs ſow our ſeed in the morning, and not ſuffer our hand to <note place="margin">Eccle. 11. 6.</note> ceaſe in the euening. Want of feruency in our loue, makes vs vnprofitable in time of need; like the Prieſt and Leuite to the <note place="margin">Luk. 10. 30 31, 32, 33.</note> man that was wounded and halfe dead, they looked on, and perhaps pitied him, but paſſed by the other way, without vouchſafing any reliefe at all: So is the common temper of mens loue, they thinke themſelues in charity, elſe God forbid, they hate no body, they hurt no body, they are no quarrellers, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe iniurious; thus they make faire wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all: but let a man fall into ſome extremity; and then they will not eaſe his burden with the leaſt of their fingers. It is Feruency muſt make our loue actiue &amp; vſefull, and which muſt make vs like the good Samaritane, miniſtring to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed as wee are able, and they haue need, <hi>Neuer turning our eyes from our owne fleſh, Eſay</hi> 58. 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:14817:68"/>
               <head>CHAP. 15. <hi>The effect of loue, with rules to diſpenſe the fruits thereof, and a complaint for the neglect of it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe religious loue thus qualified will quickly ſhew it ſelfe in the fruits and effects; it will ſweeten and ſeaſon all our actions, making vs full of mercie, and as <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 15. 14</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of the Romans full of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If you would know wherein this loue muſt and may bee diſcerned; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere euen in all things. Let all things be done in loue, is the Apoſtles direction, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 16. 14. Becauſe without this, the beſt things degenerate and turn the edge: <note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor 8. 1</note> 
                  <hi>Knowledge without loue puffeth vp.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>The gift of tongues and prophecie, without loue, is as a vaniſhing ſound.</hi> Almes without loue is oſtentation. Martyrdome without loue is fruitleſſe and vnprofitable. Let mee ſpeake it as it is; as faith without workes is dead: ſo works without loue are counterfeit and hypocriticall. <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 12. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Let loue be then without aiſsimulation,</hi> in all our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14817:68"/> which will make them paſſe more ſweetly then all the ſprings of <hi>Lebanon.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f we further inquire when and to whom this loue muſt be ſhewed, that alſo is ſet downe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10. <hi>While we haue time let vs doe good vnto all:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <note place="margin">Theophilact</note> the time of working is the time of liuing; and though there may bee diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the opportunities: yet ſhall we neuer want ſuch as will want vs. Which burden for all that, where loue is, will not ſeeme tedious. <hi>Charitas facit iugum leue:</hi> Loue makes the yoake eaſie. <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 29. 20</note> 
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured a hard ſeruice vnder <hi>Laban,</hi> of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeares for his daughter <hi>Rachel,</hi> yet they ſeemed in his eyes but a very few dayes, becauſe be loued her.</p>
               <p>If yet we further aske in what manner this loue muſt be declared: That alſo is ſet downe, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 18. <hi>Little Children, let vs not loue in word and in tongue:</hi> hee meanes, not in bare verball complement only, (for words otherwiſe muſt bee the Interpreters of the heart) but in deed and in truth; our loue muſt be reall and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall; if it be barren, it is certainly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit. If this precious treaſure be in our
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:14817:69"/> hearts, wee ought not to hide it; concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led loue is like concealed learning, vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. We muſt profeſſe it then to the comfort of our brethren, as <note n="*" place="margin">Ruth 2. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Booz</hi> ſpake to the heart of <hi>Ruth,</hi> yea and expreſſe it too as hee did: <note n="*" place="margin">Ruth 3. 18.</note> he reſted not till he had done her good in the higheſt degree. Thus <hi>Mordocai</hi> procured the wealth of his people, and ſpake peaceably to all his ſeed, <hi>Eſther</hi> 10. 3. Hee was beneficiall in word and in worke.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe generall directions, for the better diſpenſing the fruites of our loue there are certaine ſpeciall rules to be obſerued. Firſt wee muſt conſider our owne ability, and our brethrens neceſſitie, accommodating the one to the reliefe of the other, as the plaiſter to the ſore.</p>
               <p>If our ability be great, then <note n="*" place="margin">2. Cor. 9. 6.</note> by ſowing plentifully we ſhall reape plentifully, and <note n="*" place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 17.</note> lay vp a good foundation againſt the time to come. This ſheweth want of loue in thoſe who hauing great ability, doe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no good therewith; like <hi>Nabal</hi> and the rich Glutton, who had great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, euen a <note n="*" place="margin">Prou. 17. 16</note> price in the hand, but wanted a heart to vſe it. They feared to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:14817:69"/> loſe their wealth by giuing, but feared not to loſe themſelues by keeping it. If on the other ſide, our wealth be ſmall, yet if our good will bee great, it is accepted, as were the Widowes two mites, <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 3. He that is faithfull in a little enters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Maſters ioy <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 23. God crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the inward will, where he finds not the outward wealth, ſaies <hi>Auſtin.</hi> If <note place="margin">2. Cor. 8. 12</note> there be a willing mind, it is accepted by him who iudgeth not after the outward appearance, but beholdeth the heart. Yea though ſome muſt ſay with <note n="*" place="margin">Iob. 42. 8, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Peter, Siluer</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Acts 3. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and gold haue I none;</hi> yet loue is as effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, in diſpenſing the ſpirituall talent as the temporall. Thoſe who haue not the worldly goods, may be helpfull and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, by powring out faithfull prayers, as <hi>Iob</hi> did for his three friends: or by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring a word of counſaile, admonition, or exhortation at our need. He that doth ſo, may turne a ſinner from going aſtray, hee may <hi>ſaue a ſoule from death, and couer a multitude of ſinnes. Iam.</hi> 5. 20. Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie muſt bee improued according to the condition of it: which that it may be with ſucceſſe, we muſt alſo conſider the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:14817:70"/> of thoſe with whom wee haue to deale. Loue trauailes in paine with ſome, <hi>till Chriſt be formed in them,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> did <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 19.</note> with the Galathians; with others it is weake; to ſome it ſtoops; it raiſeth it ſelfe to others: <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. de catechiz. rudib. cap.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>alijs blanda, alijs ſeuera, nulli inimica, omnibus mater:</hi> gentle to ſome, ſeuere to others, an enemy to none, a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to all. Some haue more need of our prayers then of our purſe, of our counſaile then of our commodities, of our good example then of our goods. <hi>Paul</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Act. 20 33.</note> craues neither ſiluer nor gold, nor raiment, but <note n="*" place="margin">Eph. 6. 19 Col. 4. 3. 2. Theſ. 3. 1. </note> prayers often and with importunitie. <hi>Dauid</hi> on the other ſide craues not <hi>Nabals</hi> counſaile, <note n="*" place="margin">1. Sam. 25. 8.</note> but a ſupply of things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, when hee might haue ſpared it. As one member ſerues another according to the neceſſity of it, ſo ſhould we. Becauſe by how much more fitly wee apply our ſelues to one another: by ſo much more feelingly is God glorified by the party that is ſuccoured, <hi>Iob.</hi> 31. 20.</p>
               <p>After ability in the author, and neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the obiect of beneuolence obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the next rule pertaineth vnto order. All things are comely in their order,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:14817:70"/> and loue is orderly and diſcreet, <hi>non agit indecorè,</hi> it deales not vnſeemely, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 5. The orderly courſe in diſpoſing the fruits of loue is, that (where preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion impoſeth not a neceſſitie) the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall duties of loue ſhould be conferred, where there are the principall bonds of nature or grace, or other reſpects of ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie or vicinitie: ſpecially where there is an eminencie of deſert at our hands. The caſe may ſo be put that a beaſt muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued before a man: yet other things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like, wee muſt ſpecially doe good to <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> the houſe-hold of faith.</p>
               <p>A cup of cold water thus beſtowed is not forgotten, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 42. but ſhall bee remembred in the day of accounts, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 40. Euen among theſe, loue ordered by diſcretion leads to our ſpeciall charge. <hi>Integer rerum aeſtimator eſt, qui</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de doc. Chr. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 27, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>ordinatam habet dilectionem: nam quum omnibus prodeſſe non poſsis, his potiſsimum conſulendum eſt; qui conſtrictius tibi quaſi quadam ſorte coniunguntur.</hi> He is an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right eſteemer of things that hath an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly charitie: for ſeeing thou canſt not doe all men good, prouiſion muſt chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:14817:71"/> be made for thoſe, who are as it were, by a certaine lot, moſt nearely ioined vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> prouides for his Parents in the midſt of his perſecution: Our Sauiour for <note place="margin">1. Sam. 22. 3.</note> his <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 19. 26, 27.</note> mother in the midſt of his paſſion. But the bowels of compaſſion are for the moſt part chiefly moued, when the ſtate of the Church is vnder the eye of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted men, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122. <hi>Amos</hi> 7. 2. 5. <hi>Ieremie</hi> 9. 1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſuch men are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rare, the moſt euen of profeſſors, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelues abundantly, if their perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſtate be good, and if there bee plenty within their priuate walles, neuer looke further at the diſtreſſed abroad: nor at well deſeruing men of Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth: thinking becauſe charity beginnes at home, they neede not ſtraine themſelues with ſupporting ſuch as fall not within the domeſticall verge. But theſe men are much deceiued; For though it be true, that charity beginnes at home; Yet it muſt not alſo end at home, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer goe further. For as parents and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren claime their portion in vs, ſo doth the Church and Common-Wealth alſo:
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:14817:71"/> ſpecially ſuch as haue deſerued our loue, to whom, perhaps we owe euen our ſelues <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. ver. 19</note> as <hi>Philemon</hi> did to <hi>Paul.</hi> 
               </p>
               <p>Can that loue be religious, which is ſo ſtraitned in the bowels of compaſſion, as that it will not inlarge it ſelfe to the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted? Or is that loue religious, which can be vnthankfull to men of ſpeciall merit, for temporall or ſpirituall ſeruice? Let charity beginne where it ought, but let it not both beginne and end in one Period. If it be naturally diffuſiue, confine it not to one point or center, which ought to liue and moue, and worke in the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence round about.</p>
               <p>The third rule in the exerciſe of loue concerneth thoſe who are without, or at leaſt farther off. <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> Wee muſt haue peace and concord with all, ſo far as is poſſible: our God is the God of peace, not of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. 33.</note> or confuſion; and when he exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited himſelfe to <hi>Eliah,</hi> he was not in the <note place="margin">1. King. 19. 11.</note> mighty wind, nor in the Earth-quake, nor in the fire, but in the ſtill and quiet voice: to ſhew that hee is not among tumults and quarrells, but where peace, and vnitie, and amity is imbraced. Yet he that muſt
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:14817:72"/> endeuour to haue peace with all is not bound to haue ſocietie, nor ordinarie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe of conſultations and familiarity with all, nor peace neither, further then may ſtand with holineſſe and godly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. For what if there be ineuitable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of a breach? What if a man will needs become an enemy? and prouoke vs with heauy iniuries? Here now is loue put to the greateſt tryall, yet will it bee fruitfull, and that in ſeaſon. For Chriſtian loue may as truly be exerciſed to an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as to a friend: and in forgiuing iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as in giuing gifts. Did not <hi>Steuens</hi> charity ſhine as cleerely, <note n="*" place="margin">Acts 7. 60. Acts 6. 6</note> in praying for the forgiueneſſe of his perſecutors, when he ſuffered as a Martyr, as in miniſtring to the neceſſities of the Saints as a Deacon? Forgiueneſſe is like a bloſſome in March, that ſhrinkes not at a nipping blaſt, this will proue the forwardeſt and goodlieſt fruit in Autume. But what if forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be not ſought by him that doth the wrong? yet muſt thou daily aske forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at Gods hands vnder condition of forgiuing. What if the iniurie be daily multiplyed and renewed? Heauen is open
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:14817:72"/> to thy complaints, and the Law is open to reſtraine intollerable perſons, onely in ſuits at Law, when they are ineuitable. Loue firſt retaineth an vnfeined deſire of peace, though it be prouoked. Secondly, it abſtaineth from priuate reuenge, though it haue opportunitie. Thirdly, true loue prayeth for the enemies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, though continuing refractary.</p>
               <p>But here may I iuſtly take vp a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint; <hi>Charitatem in terris peregrinam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere.</hi> As one ſpeakes of Truth: ſo may I of Charitie, that it liues as a ſtranger here on earth; little religious loue is to bee found in the world. Some men loue no body but for ſome carnall reſpects. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers can loue any, but the ſeruants of God; as <hi>Achab</hi> could like well of all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, but of <hi>Michaiah</hi> and <hi>Eliah,</hi> and <note place="margin">1 King. 22. 68. 1 King. 21. 20.</note> them he hated, and counted them as ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Others that can find no fault in Gods children, yet hold off their loue in ſuſpence; and they muſt know them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, before they will ioyne with them in amitie and ſocietie, and ſo perhaps they neuer meete. Others confine their loue to ſocietie in reuelling &amp; laſciuiouſneſſe,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:14817:73"/> or ſome other rudeneſſe in which there is at laſt but a bond of iniquitie. So little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement finds loue vpon earth: yet it is the bond of perfection, both in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and in earth, and hath the moſt noble teſtimonie and ſtile to be called in this place, <hi>the fulfilling of the Law.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 16. <hi>That loue is a fulfilling of the Law accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of it, and that yet hence it doth not follow: either that the perfect ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Law is poſsible in this life: or that any can be iuſtified by the workes of the Law, in this ſtate of corruption.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOr hee that loueth another hath fulfilled the Law.]</hi> Theſe words are a reaſon of the former exhortation. The argument is thus. The mutuall loue of Chriſtians is the fulfilling of the Law, therefore wee ought to loue one another. When loue is ſaid, Cantic. 8. 6. to bee ſtrong as death: <hi>non potuit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſtin) Charitatis fortitudo magnificentiùs exprimi, quàm</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:14817:73"/> 
                  <hi>quòd morti comparatur:</hi> The ſtrength of loue could not be more magnifically ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, then when it is compared vnto death. As he ſaith of the ſtrength of loue, that it could not be expreſſed in more loftie termes: ſo may I ſay of the ſupere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent excellencie of loue, it could not be ſet downe in higher termes, then in calling it the fulfilling of the Law. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which words ſundry things may be enquired, both for the meaning and certaintie of them. As firſt, the thing in hand being mutuall charitie and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue which is limited and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the ſecond table of the Law, and is no further extended; how the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it can bee ſaid to fulfill the Law? ſeeing in this dutie (ſuppoſed as good as can bee in this life) a man one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fulfilleth the ſecond table of the Law.</p>
               <p>The anſwer herein is this: that though he that loueth his neighbour intirely, do but fulfill the ſecond table expreſly, yet he performes the firſt alſo by neceſſarie conſequence. For all religious loue to men floweth originally from our loue to
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:14817:74"/> God: and our loue to God dependeth wholly on his loue to vs. <note n="*" place="margin">1 Ioh. 4. 19</note> 
                  <hi>We loue him becauſe he loued vs firſt.</hi> As therefore a great brightneſſe of the ayre at midnight, argueth the ſhining of the Moone, and that preſumeth an illumination from the Sunne, becauſe theſe depend one on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: ſo the diffuſing of our charitie on our neighbours proueth our loue to God, and our loue to God preſumeth his loue to vs firſt, for the inſeparable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance which they haue on each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. We may alſo briefly anſwer, that our brotherly loue fulfilleth the Law, that is, that part of the Law which doth punctually require it.</p>
               <p>The other queſtions ariſe from the ambiguitie of the ſpeech, <hi>Hath fulfilled the Law.</hi> Out of which our aduerſaries draw two concluſions. Firſt, that the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Law is poſſible in this life. Secondly, that a Chriſtian may be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the workes of the Law.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, the Rhemiſts in their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall notes vpon theſe words ſay this. Here we learne that the Law may bee, and is fulfilled by loue in this life, againſt
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:14817:74"/> our aduerſaries, who ſay, it is impoſſible to keepe the Commandements. The ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument may thus be framed. He that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth another, or that loueth his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour fulfilleth the Law. But euery true Chriſtian can, and muſt, and doth loue his neighbour; therefore euery true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian can, and muſt fulfill the Law. Firſt, to the propoſition I ſay, that he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth another fulfilleth the Law, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the qualitie and meaſure of his loue. <hi>Qualis &amp; quanta dilectio, talis &amp; tanta eſt legis impletio:</hi> ſo farre as he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, ſo farre he fulfilleth the Law. But ſay they, in the aſſumption; euery good Chriſtian can, and may, and doth loue his neighbour. To this I anſwer, that loue is either perfect and full in the affections and offices of it, without any errour or defect at all: this is that which fulfilleth the Law, according to the ſeueritie of it to the vttermoſt, but it is impoſſible in this life through the weakeneſſe of the fleſh. There is another loue which is true, ſincere, and heartie, yet not without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, for in many things we all fall ſhort in affections, in actions, <note n="*" place="margin">Gal 5. 17</note> 
                  <hi>The fleſh</hi>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:14817:75"/> 
                  <hi>luſteth against the ſpirit, and the ſpirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fleſh, ſo that we cannot do as wee would.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 13.</note> I haue not (ſaith <hi>Paul)</hi> attained vnto perfection. This loue is poſſible, but not perfect, the other is perfect, but not poſſible to vs compaſſed as we are with imperfections; and conſequently the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect impletion of the Law in this life is not poſſible.</p>
               <p>The ſecond argument depends on this, framed by thoſe, who by building iuſtification vpon the workes of the Law, put themſelues vpon the hazard of falling from grace. The argument is thus. Hee that fulfilleth the Law is iuſtified thereby; according to that word, <note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 3. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>He that doth theſe things ſhall liue by them.</hi> But euerie true Chriſtian fulfilleth the Law by loue; therefore euery true Chriſtian is iuſtified by the Law. <hi>Stapleton</hi> propounds it thus <note place="margin">Stapleton Antidot.</note> in ſenſe, and triumpheth like a conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour againſt <hi>Caluin</hi> and <hi>Beza.</hi> His argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is thus. The fulfilling of the Law is true righteouſneſſe; but he that loueth his neighbour fulfilleth the Law; therefore he that loueth his neighbour obtaineth true righteouſneſſe, or true iuſtification thereby.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:14817:75"/>
               <p> The ſtrength of theſe arguments is in the ambiguitie of the phraſe: for true it is; He that fulfilleth the Law ſhall be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied thereby, if he fulfill it in all points per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly; otherwiſe not iuſtification, but malediction is of the Law. But he that loueth his neighbour fulfilleth the Law. That I grant is true, he that loueth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly without any defect fulfilleth the Law perfectly; but where is that man, that euer ſo loued, or obſerued the Law without errour or imperfection?</p>
               <p>Was there euer Patriarke, Prophet, or Apoſtle without ſinne?</p>
               <p>Doth not <hi>Dauid</hi> the man after Gods owne heart confeſſe this ſinne with much contrition againſt himſelfe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 5. and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</p>
               <p>Doth not <note n="*" place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Daniel</hi> the like againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and all the people?</p>
               <p>Doth not <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> after his conuerſion yet lament his vnwilling ſubiection vnto ſinne? When the beſt of men condemne themſelues, is it not impudent pride in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to iuſtifie himſelfe by the workes of the Law? Can any bee ſo partiall in his owne cauſe, or ſo ſenſleſſe of his owne
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:14817:76"/> eſtate, as not to tremble at his dayly tranſgreſſions, ariſing from the ſinke of originall corruption?</p>
               <p>I know for the opening of this ſpeech in hand, the learned bring this diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. There is, <hi>impletio legis quoad partes,</hi> or <hi>quoad gradus;</hi> We fulfill the Law ſay they, according to the parts, or according to the degrees. According to the parts, when we haue reſpect to all the commandements, as well in one thing as in another, not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing our ſelues in the neglect or breach of any; thus farre ſay they we attaine. But according to the degrees or perfection required in the ſtrict letter of the Law, (for which cauſe it is called the killing letter,) ſo we do not fulfil the Law.</p>
               <p>In this diſtinction ſome ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but for mine owne part I am of opinion, that the beſt men faile, not onely in the degrees, but euen in the parts of the Law, omitting at ſome time the very duties of loue by infirmitie, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, negligence, or temptation, ſo that our beſt fulfilling of the Law is, when that which is not fulfilled is forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: according to that of <hi>Auſtin, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:14817:76"/> 
                  <hi>mandata Dei tunc implentur, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do quod non fit, ignoſcitur;</hi> All the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God are then fulfilled, when that is forgiuen which is not fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. And our beſt iuſtification is; <hi>Quando fides impetrat, quod Lex imperat:</hi> When faith obtaineth in Ieſus Chriſt that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect righteouſneſſe, which the Law en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyneth by a liuely application of the ſame to the conſcience. As our loue is not perfect in regard of our defects in matter, meaſure, and circumſtance: ſo it cannot be meritorious, becauſe it is a debt, and ſuch a debt as is neuer fully payd, but ſtill remaineth due. No debt is merit; <hi>Eſt ae natura meriti, vt ſit opus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debitum, pramium ex indebito faciens debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> It is of the nature of merit, that it be a work not due, &amp; which makes the reward being nor due of it ſelfe, due to the doer.</p>
               <p>Is all our labour of loue then loſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is vnperfect? and becauſe our ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Law is vnperfect? or becauſe when wee haue done our beſt, yet our loue is not meritorious? or becauſe our beſt fulfilling of the Law, is but onely a true and ſincere obſeruation of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:14817:77"/> but not a full obedience of the Law <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in exactnes? Is all our labour I ſay then loſt? God forbid: for though wee cannot attaine vnto perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this life, it is reſerued for the next: our righteouſneſſe being here eclipſed with manifold defects: yet the neerer wee come vnto it, the more conformable we are to God, and to his Law, then which nothing is more beautifull, or more bleſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> profeſſeth that though hee had <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 12. 14.</note> not as yet attained, yet he aſpired with great indeauour, and preſſed toward the mark, for the price of the high calling of God in CHRIST IESVS: euen ſo ſhould wee doe alſo, who come much ſhorter of perfection then he did: the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of ſin continuing more, &amp; the Image of Chriſt being leſſe renued &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored in vs then in him. We ſhould, I ſay with all our ſtrength &amp; intention of ſpirit, ſtriue to be aduanced to a higher pitch &amp; meaſure of grace, of goodnes, of loue with the fruites therof; knowing that loue is the <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 13. 35. </note> marke of Gods children: the proofe of <note n="*" place="margin">1 Iohn 47.</note> our regeneration: the ſeale of our tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:14817:77"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 Ioh. 3. 14.</note> from death to life: yea ſuch an euidence hereof as will ſhew it ſelfe and ſtand vpon record in the effects, when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſignes may faile in the day of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: knowing alſo that hatred, which is contrary hereunto, is the diuels <note n="*" place="margin">1 Ioh. 3. 10. Ioh. 2. 11.</note> brand on the veſſels of wrath; he that hateth his brother walketh in darkneſſe, and kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not whether he goeth, becauſe dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath blinded his eyes, euen his iudgement, the eye of the inner man. For <note n="*" place="margin">Auſtin &amp; gloſſa ordin.</note> 
                  <hi>Ira eſt feſtuca, odium eſt trabs in oculo;</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is a moate, but hatred is a beame in the eye.</p>
               <p>The ſumme is this. Debts muſt be pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to whom they are due. Loue is a Debt; therefore it muſt be paid to all, as time, and place, and power doe permit: that by yeelding hereof in obedience to the Commandement, our loue to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe may appeare, <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 14, 15.</note> who meaſures our loue by our obedience. Who if he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the readineſſe of the ſpirit, though the fleſh bee weake: if a promiſing and chearefull heart, though ability bee not great, hee will drawe vs on to further proofe.</p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:14817:78"/>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 15. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Euery branch that beareth fruit hee purgeth it, that it may bring forth more fruit,</hi> to the honour and glory of his owne name, and to the benefit of his Elect.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:14817:78"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. <hi>line</hi> 15. for tooke <hi>reade</hi> take. p. 12. <hi>l.</hi> 12. for haereditale <hi>r.</hi> haereditate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 35. <hi>l.</hi> 2. for ſilences <hi>r.</hi> ſilence. p. 43. <hi>l.</hi> 16. for euer <hi>r,</hi> ends p. 47. <hi>l.</hi> 16. for founders <hi>r</hi> foundreſs. p. 56. <hi>l.</hi> 23. for mutant. <hi>r</hi> mutent. p. 61. <hi>l.</hi> 11. for no, <hi>r.</hi> a. p. 67. <hi>l.</hi> 13. for ofter, <hi>r.</hi> often p 92. <hi>l</hi> 14. for ſaueurs <hi>r.</hi> ſauers p. 95. <hi>l.</hi> 7. add to the end of the <hi>l.</hi> ſubſtance. p. 99 for moderate <hi>r</hi> immoderate. p 103. <hi>l.</hi> 9. for which <hi>r.</hi> whom. p 125. <hi>l.</hi> 1. for doing <hi>r.</hi> doings. in the <hi>Marg,</hi> for <hi>Theophilact,</hi> 1. <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact.</hi> p. 139. <hi>l.</hi> 16. for this, <hi>r.</hi> his.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
